<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A straunge foot-post vvith a packet full of strange petitions. After a long vacation for a good terme.</title>
            <author>Nixon, Anthony.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08256</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18591</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110172</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845775</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845775</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10696</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08256)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10696)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 855:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A straunge foot-post vvith a packet full of strange petitions. After a long vacation for a good terme.</title>
                  <author>Nixon, Anthony.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[52] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By E[dward] A[llde] dwelling neare Christ-Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: Anthony Nixon.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-G⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10696:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10696:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Straunge Foot-Poſt, <hi>VVith</hi> A Packet full of ſtrange <hi>Petitions.</hi> After a long Vacation for a good Terme.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Printed at London by E.A. dwelling neare Chriſt Church. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:10696:2"/>
            <head>THE PETITIONERS.</head>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>The Harlot. To her the Bawde comes.</item>
                  <item>The Spendall. On him the Sergeant attends.</item>
                  <item>The Countrey Client. The Hoſtler followes him.</item>
                  <item>The Old Seruingman, followed by the Widdow.</item>
                  <item>The Maide gotten with childe. The Parriter waites on her.</item>
                  <item>The Louer. To whom the countrey Schoolemaſter comes.</item>
                  <item>The Old Woman married to the yong man.</item>
                  <item>The Young woman married to the old man.</item>
                  <item>The Cuckold.</item>
                  <item>The Old Souldier.</item>
                  <item>The Prentiſe.</item>
                  <item>The Mal-content.</item>
                  <item>The Poore Scoller.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10696:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>Perſians</hi> were wont to keepe in their houſes the Picture of an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picure</hi> ouerladen with wine, and ſleeping with meate in his mouth, that by the view of ſuch an vgly fight they might learne to be moderate, and avoyd the like exceſſe. The <hi>Parthians</hi> alſo to make their young men learne and fall into deteſtation of the alluring inticements of wicked women, are ſaid to keepe in their houſes a young man blinde carued very curiouſly; beſides whome, was adioyned the Picture of a Woman, of farre more excellent perfection then the Image of <hi>Pigmalion,</hi> hauing one hand in his pocket to picke his purſe, and holding a knife in the other hand to cut his throat.</p>
            <p>For eſchewing the like enormities, I wiſh thee <hi>(Reader)</hi> in ſtead of the <hi>Perſians</hi> Picture of an <hi>Epicure,</hi> and the <hi>Parthians</hi> Picture of an <hi>Harlot</hi> in thine houſe, to carry about thee this <hi>Packet</hi> in thy Pocket: Which being opened, will Preſent ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient matter vnto thee that may both make thee weane thy ſelfe from wanton deſires, and ſhun the miſery that followes exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue ſuperfluity, as alſo eſcape many other detriments that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the contempt of aduiſed courſes.</p>
            <p>If any handling this <hi>Packe,</hi> or peruſing it (as I doubt not but many will) ſhall by it be drawne to forſake ſome infectious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours that it opens vnto them, I ſhall be glad of the recouery ſuch ſicke Patients: If others (not tainted) with the like infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities) ſhall onely looke on it, and laugh at it, and partly like it, the end of my labours haue a condigne counterpoiſe: Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine Anthony Nixon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10696:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10696:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A STRANGE FOOTE-POST, WITH A PACKET full of madde Petitions.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Uſt about that time of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yeare when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Spring</hi> begins to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand her hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maide <hi>Flora,</hi> to ſticke the boſome of euery watry maedow, &amp; ſedgie lake, with noſegayes of party coloured flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers: hauing dulled my ſpirits with ſerious meditations, and plunged my ſenſes in the quickſands of <hi>Inuention,</hi> aſwell, to ſhake of a ſullen <hi>Melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> that attended me, as to entertaine ſome quicke, and more publicke recreation: I walked into a neighbouring mends, where it was my chance to light vpon an Arbor ſo priuately ſeated, as if <hi>Nature</hi> had built it a Caue, or receptacle for <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude:</hi> inuironed ſo cloſe, with the long and ſlender armes of <hi>Oſiers,</hi> and ſo curiouſly intermingled with the leauy fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of <hi>Woodbine,</hi> and ſwéere <hi>Eglantine,</hi> that neither cold nor rains could eaſily pieree <hi>it.</hi> In whoſe windowes, the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered <hi>Quiriſters</hi> of the grous, ſkipping from twig to twig, ſong pretty (though idle) notes, to the murmure of a ſiluer ſpring, which made ſuch ſoft and ſolemne Muſicke, that what with wondering, at the more then common worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of <hi>Art,</hi> and the <hi>Metaphiſicall</hi> indeauours of <hi>Nature,</hi> in their ignorant (yet well according <hi>Harmony,</hi> Leaning my hand vpon my elbow, (being at that time deſtitute of a ſof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pillow) I fell into a ſodaine, yet ſound ſléeps, during which, my imaginary inſight apprehended a moſt ſtrange viſion.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10696:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Wée thought I was eleuated into the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> where like a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ſtranger caſt vpon a forrain Coaſt, I was ſtricken with vn-vtterable admiration, wondring at the ſtrange obiectes I beheld. Gazing thus on euery ſide, like a Country-Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman at her firſt comming to a famous Citty, one clapt me vpon the head, whoſe very ſight did much affright me, that it was enough to haue put me out of the wit I had: For the party I ſpeake of was headed like <hi>Hydra,</hi> hauing more Tongues,<note place="margin">The deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> then <hi>Eſope</hi> prouided for his Maiſters dinner: and for eyes, he was no <hi>Cyclops,</hi> or Polypheme, but an other <hi>Argus:</hi> The cloathes he wore, were for all the world faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned like a fantaſticall <hi>Engliſhmans,</hi> a gallim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>ry of moſt Countrie cuts, but not of one Cloath, Stuffe, Sattin, Vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet, &amp;c. as theirs are: Nor of one, two, three, foure colours, as for the moſt part theirs are; but heere a péece of Veluet, there a peece of Vellure, heere a péece of Sattin, there a péece of Sackcloath, filled with ſundry patches of ſeuerall pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes, like a Taylors hole, or rather Hell, whereinto he caſteth many bodies of men and women.</p>
            <p>This Monſter ſeeing me ſo pittifully perplexed, told me that he was not ſo terrible as he ſeemed, and that his name was <hi>Opinion,</hi> ſo Headed, Sighted, Tongued and arraied, to ſhew the multiplicity, variety, and contrariety of mens <hi>Opinions,</hi> Fantaſies, and Conceipts: And that the place wherein I then was was named the <hi>Metrapolitan</hi> Cittie of the World, ſeeming indeed like Heauen it ſelfe, inhabited by Spirits of all ſortes, adorned with Sunne and Moone, like a contributarie King and Queene: Out about with all the Signes of the <hi>Zodiack</hi> garniſhed with Planets, which like Rulers ouerſwayed Sublunary Creatures: Beautified with Starres of thrée fortes, whereof ſome were tearmed <hi>Fixae,</hi> reſembing vertuous and conſtant women, kéeping in their <hi>Sphaeres,</hi> as in their houſes. Others <hi>Errantes,</hi> wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Starres, gadding like Goſſips, which ride from Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to Countries, running from their owne Manſions to Tauernes, from their huſbands boſoms to other mens beds.
<pb facs="tcp:10696:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>The third, <hi>Cadentes,</hi> that is, falling Starres, whereunto wantons may his compared, which fall from the Heauen of Honeſty, to the immoveable maſſe of Miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="7 letters">
                  <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
               </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and immodeſty: Forthwith he led mee through many La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es and ſhewed me the ſignes as wee paſſed along the heauen ſtreete: Here (ſaid hee) is <hi>Aries,</hi> the ſigne of the <hi>Ramme:</hi> What the <hi>Ramme</hi> in floor ſtreet thought I. This is <hi>Cancer</hi> the ſigne of the <hi>Crabbe:</hi> Here is <hi>Virgo,</hi> the ſigne of the <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de:</hi> That is a rare ſigne indeede, many a young beginner would be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> glad to dwell at that ſigne: This is <hi>Scorpio,</hi> the ſigne of the Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, a venemous Serpent which hurteth with the farie: That is <hi>Capricornua,</hi> the ſigne of the Goates head, ſome Cuckold languiſheth there, while his wife laugheth abroad: This is <hi>Gemin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the ſigne of the Twinnes, there dwelleth a good member in the Commonwealth, which getteth two at once: Héere is <hi>Leo</hi> the ſigne of the Lyon: There is <hi>Libra,</hi> the ſigne of the paire of Sea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les: <hi>Terras Aſtraea reliquit, Iuſtice</hi> hath forſaken the Garth, and kéepeth ſhopp there: That is <hi>Sagittarius</hi> the ſigne of the Archer, binde <hi>Cupid</hi> maketh bird bolts there to daile Woodcocks: This is <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quarius,</hi> the ſigne of the Water bearer, I ſuppoſed at firſt a Vintener dwelled there, which cartieth ſo much water to quench the fire, which would elſe riſe out of his Seller, till I gazed for a Buſh and could ſoe none, but the buſh Beard of a Brewer: After he conducted me by the ſeauen Planets ſeauen Gates of this Cittie: The firſt and laweſt he called <hi>Luna,</hi> which being then in the Ecclips,<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>odern</note> I deemed the <hi>Poſtern Gate</hi> ſhut cloſe: The ſecond <hi>Sol</hi> the Sunne, which I reſeen bled to <hi>Mooregate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Moor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> becauſe it is more delicious and pleaſant then the Moone, with beames and rayes, or rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>avies on the one ſide: The third <hi>Mercury</hi> the God of Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ues, Cheaters, Nymble-ſingered fellowes, which made me call it <hi>Newgate:</hi> The fourth <hi>Venus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">New<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gate Laug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the Goddeſſe of Laue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which I tearmed <hi>Allgate,</hi> becauſe all goe thorough that Gate: The fiſt <hi>Mars,</hi> which loo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed ſternly like King <hi>Lad,</hi> whoſe very aſpect at that time wrought in my concerpt that
<pb facs="tcp:10696:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>I feard a Sergeant was dragging mee to <hi>Lud-gate:</hi> The ſixt <hi>Iupiter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alderſgate.</note> which I ſurmiſd to be <hi>Alderſ-gate:</hi> The ſeauenth <hi>Saturne,</hi> elde, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ble, and deerepit, which I thought might ſomwhat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tly be nominated <hi>Cripple-gate:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cripplegate</note> Are here all ſaid I? I haue one gate yet, ſtanding boyd to bee ſhut vp with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>titude: What gate is that ſaid <hi>Opinion?</hi> It is <hi>Biſhops-gate</hi> ſaid I. Some Philoſophers cauill about it ſaid <hi>Opinion.</hi> But <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Plato</hi> make reckoning of are eight, which is called <hi>Sphaera octaua,</hi> that is, the firmament containing the fired ſtarres. Why then this <hi>Sphaera Octaua</hi> is <hi>Biſhopgate,</hi> containing all the fired ſtarres: that is, the faithfull <hi>Miniſters:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Biſhops gate.</note> And the Philoſophers which cauill about it are none but contentious <hi>Browniſts,</hi> and <hi>Separaters:</hi> which becauſe the eyes of their true vnderſtanding are pluckt out, would plucke the whole houſe vpon their owne deads, to the ouerthrow of the Rulers. But let theſe <hi>Byaſes</hi> paſſe by like aſſes, with bag &amp; baggage to <hi>Anſer-dame,</hi> ſo long as we haue <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> the Prince of Philoſophers, and <hi>Plato</hi> the Diuine on our ſides. Our gardens will proſper the better when they haue in them not one of theſe <hi>Elders,</hi> whereupon ſo many couetous <hi>Iudaſſes</hi> bang themſelues.</p>
            <p>By this time we had paſied through al the Planets ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with ſtars, like ſo many gates with watchmen; &amp; were entred into the are the heauens ſuburbs: Here (quoth <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi>) you may daily beheld diuers that paſſe to &amp; fro from all parts to preſent their ſcueral petitions to <hi>Fortune,</hi> &amp; implore her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for ſome good hap: which many times they obtaine, if their Petitions go not through many hands: for then they are either loſt or torn or ſome to ſome friends hands, againſt whom they are preſerred, and the Petitioners a recheckt and called ſeditions knaues, and go home perhaps an hundred miles with a Flea in their eare.</p>
            <p>Then me thought I was very importunate to know the ſeuer all ſuiters, that becau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſo ſuppliant to <hi>Fortune:</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as <hi>Opinion</hi> was telling me he would certifie me of them in order, Behold (quoth he) yonder is one trauelling a pace,
<pb facs="tcp:10696:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>that miniſters matter to giue you ſome ſatisfaction. And as I was thus giuing my attendance, and obſeruation, I might ſee a ſemall comming, indeed a peart one ſhe was, as ready to giue the welcome to her cuſtomers, as a boy in a barre, and as nimble as a Paraſite in an old Comedie.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The harlot paſſeth by them.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Harlot.</note>FIe vpon her (ſaid I) ſhe will neuer haue good ſucceſſe in her ſuite, ſhe hath ſuch Anticke attice, and doſh ſo trip &amp; go with her <hi>Petition:</hi> What? a woman of tall ſtature and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right body? (would ſhe were as vpright in her life &amp; beham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our) high browes, faire haire? hath ſhe not robbed the dead for it)? round chéeks curt all lips, dimpled chin, ſleeke necke, &amp; ſlender waſte? Tis good if they be not hooks to draw men in, &amp; birdlime to tie the feathers of euery ſtranger, that nons may eſcape them. But I feare ſhe is (as ſome ſay of wanton wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) like <hi>Circes</hi> witches, and can turne vame glorius footes into Aſſes, gluttonous fooles into Swine, pleaſant fooles in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Apes, proud fooles into Peacocks, and when ſhe hath done, ſcourge them out of dores with a w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>This is one (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) whoſe face is a painted Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, whereas her mind is a Toinbe full of rotten bones and Serpents:<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>inion or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Harlot.</note> her browes like the Diamond) containe vertue to relieue, and poyſon to kill: her lookes are like Calenders, that can determine no certainty, but as a certaine leaſe) which is moſt drie, when it lookes moſt mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt: ſo when ſhee ſmiles, ſhe imagines deceit, and her laugnters are tempered with enuy &amp; reuenge: her vows are but as words written in the wind: her promiſes Caracters figured in the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, figures grauen in the Snow, which are blowne with the wind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> melted with the Sun: and her loue, like the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of a Serpent ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r a ſtone, which once paſt, can neuer vs ſeene. She will promiſe mountainies, and perform Moie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is. She will ſay ſhe loues with <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>o,</hi> and yet fame with <hi>Cren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da:</hi> follow <hi>Demophon</hi> with <hi>Phillis,</hi> and yet vs more ſtrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb facs="tcp:10696:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>then <hi>Luna:</hi> ſhe hath ſmiles (at her wiſh) to bewitch, and teares (at command) as the <hi>Crocodile,</hi> to betray. If thou proffer her any thing, ſhe will poc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee at all: if thou haſt gold, ſhe is a Horſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>each, and will not out of thy boſome: but ſhée hates an empty purſe, as the <hi>Hyenna</hi> doth the ſight of a man, and wil ſhe from thée, when thou art poore, as the foule from the Fauhon. In plaine termes, ſhe is a proud prorhane Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot. And were ſhe not prophane, what Athieſt would frequent her? were ſhe not bawdy, what <hi>Puncquatero</hi> would ſhew his rotten téeth to her? Were ſhe not ridiculous, what country Gentiles would come to her? Were ſhe not full of toyes and gewgawes, what Citizens would flocke to her? In a word, Were ſhe not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as ſhe is, ſhe would be like a Politician with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a profound head, like a flatterer without a glib tougue, like an Aſtronamer without eyes, a Muſitian without hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, a Souldier without hands, a Porter without a ſtrong backe, a Gentleman vſher without ſtraitelegs, a Lackey without féete, in no reputation. But it is not ſo with her, for ſhe is a <hi>Bona Roga:</hi> and the Petition which ſhe comes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, muſt needs (no doubt) bring ſome good fruite, from that corrupt trée.</p>
               <div type="petition">
                  <p>Vouchſafe to looke vpon the lines of your humble Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, who from fifteene yeares of age hath hene a woman of no carriage,<note place="margin">The Harlots Petition.</note> liuing alwaies chaſt both in towne and countrey, and haue had much dealing with many of great ability, till of late that I failed of your furtherance, and miſſed many of my cuſtomers. For whom, when I made a ſecret inquiſition, and priuie ſearch (fearing they had made a voyage to ſettle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in <hi>Virginia</hi>) I met ſome of them prepared for Tiburne, others I found enconntred with Counters, and ſome laid vp in houſes of Hoſpitalitie: which vnexpected ſight did ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pale me, that forthwith I thought good to preſent this Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnto you: requeſting that ſuch as are my welwillers, may haue ſome longer continuance of your fauours, and not taſt ſo ſodainly of your frownes, (which will be my vtter vndoing) ſo long as they haue money or meanes. But when they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute
<pb facs="tcp:10696:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>of both, then caſt them off, let them ſteale and be han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: which if they deny, I wiſh you ſend them farre enough: for there is nothing more comberſome, then impecunious hangets on.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Where there is one of theſe officers, I would there were twentie.</note>There be alſo ſome of the officious (to whom I wiſh none of your fauours) as the onely cauſers of our ouerthrowes. For they hunt vs like Hares, &amp; ferrit vs like Conyes. They tie vs to ſtakes like Beares, and whip vs like Iades. They driue vs from poſt to piller, that were we not predeſtinate as it were to liue chaſt, they would compell vs euen againſt our Fate to become chaſt, they do ſo chaſe vs from countrey to citie, from citie to ſuburbes, from houſes and husbands, to couſens and allies, where we leade a life like brute beaſts among graſſe, trees; &amp;c. Or liue like the old water-Nymphs, or Fairies (which pinched poore men) in wels &amp; ditches. As Shorditch &amp; Clarkenwell. I therefore ſue to haue an <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> ſerued vpon them, eſpecially certaine little Annimals, called Beagles, who ſeeing poore Does proſtrate before their feete, haue notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the heart to hurt, and draw blood from their ribbes and ſhoulders.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Maddona Meretrix.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Baude commeth to the Harlot.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Baude.</note>GOe thy wayes, thy fooles bolt is ſhot a Cockheight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſtarres, which will light vpon thine owne head. Here is a Petition indeed, if all Petitions ſhould be granted. But there is another come vnto her, ſhe ſhould be a yong woman by her great belly: but now ſhe yawneth, I ſee the marke is out of her mouth, ſhe walloweth like a Sow with pigge, talketh very imperiouſly, &amp; is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lad moſt modeſtly But I miſlike one thing, ſhe cougheth ſo ſorely, are her lungs ſound?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The opinion. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a Baude.</note>Out vpon her (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) though ſhe ſpeake purely, ſweare ſparingly, looke demurely, and walke ſagely, yet her life is loathſome, and behauior beaſtly. She hath her roguiſh
<pb facs="tcp:10696:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Rhetorick</hi> at her fingers ends, and can winch, kicke, and fling when ſhe ſéeth her oportunitie. She goeth to the Church with an ill will, vnleſſe to picke a pocket, or to peruert ſome honeſt mans wife ſhe is pued withall. But ſhe will beſtir her ſtumps to get eaſie roome in a Theater; and twenty to one ſhe will lure ſome Buſſard to dogge her home at the end of the Play. She liueth by vſury, but here is the difference: the vſurer putteth but ten (ouer &amp; aboue) to his hundreth in the yeare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But ſhe brings an hundreth to ten, nay to two ſomtimes in a weeke, Abhominable filth as ſhe is, I wiſh thée to ſtop thy eares at her words, for ſhe is a <hi>Mer-maide,</hi> or rather <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maide.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>A filthie Baude.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Spendall paſſeth along.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Spendall.</note>ROome for a Gentleman, mark the motion my Maſters: his dublet is of the ragged ranke, with neuer a button on it, and his bréeches are very faulty, they muſt be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, I maruell he buyeth hunſelfe no better cloathes now his rents begin to come in ſo faſt: Foure paire of yarn ſtock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings would make no great ſhew vpon thoſe ſpindle ſhankes: he looketh very Lentenly and commeth halting on.</p>
               <p>This tottered Colt (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) which once had high deſires,<note place="margin">The Opinion of the Spendal</note> hath now lowe fortunes; his thoughts were woont to reach at ſtarres, but now ſtumble at ſtones. He was his fathers dotage, and his Mams darling: a toward Springall you will ſay, when he lay with his mothers Chambermaide at ſixtéene: and an vntoward <hi>Spendall,</hi> when he had lauiſhed the ſixt part of a Million before he knew ſixe and twentie Birth dayes. He did of late ſwim in gluttonny, but now is pinched with pennury. He was woont to deuiſe what to eat, and is now deſtitute of any food. He hath worne more vpon his backe then the gold (which procured paſſage for the Aſſe into the Caſtle) would defray. His <hi>quondam</hi> full féeding ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him now look ſo emptily. His drinking ſo many healths hath taken all health from him: his ſo often leaping the pale, cauſeth him looke ſo pale: his cloſe following the faſhion,
<pb facs="tcp:10696:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>bringeth him now (as you ſée) out of all forme and faſhion: had he taken time before he might haue ledged in an houſe li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a palloce, as he doth now in a place like a priſon, lying like a <hi>Nutmeg in a Grate,</hi> being the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me of vnthriſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe, the <hi>Hierogliphicke of Riot,</hi> the picture of the <hi>Prodigall,</hi> and the <hi>Indiuidium vagum</hi> of a poore pitifull pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ileſſe <hi>Spendall.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="petition">
                  <p>Moſt humbly ſueth a caſhierd Caualiere, no Gentleman yet a knights ſonne and heire, being richly bequeached,<note place="margin">The Spendals Petition.</note> and well mannered, conſorted with men of choice faſhion, with women of ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us report: much indebted to merchants, and greatly bound to their wiues. But at laſt wanting preſent meanes to repay the one, and competent matter to come euen with the other, which did put me to my plunges, that I was conſtrained to colleague with a Miſer, <hi>Qui nummos adm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi> An vſurer that doth make much of money, who vpon ſome conſideration of my good conditions did ſupply me for a time, but when Doomes-day came, that I ſhould render an account for all, all was gone, my lands were ſeiſed vpon, my credite ceaſed, and I clapped vp amongſt Bank<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pes, and bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowers: where now I muſt lie like a forlorne wretch, eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to die for want of reliefe: my friends pittie me, my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies play vpon me. All ſhe from me, none come nye me, but mercileſſe keepers, and miſerable caytiſſes,<note place="margin">The end of Riot.</note> who make me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what I learned long agoe.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Cum fuctis foelix mult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s numer abis amicos,</l>
                     <l>Nullus ad amiſſas ibit amicus opes.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>When I was mounted vpon the chariot of Fortune. Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap> would conuerſe with me, Lawyers giue attendance to my ſuites, Tradeſmen cappe to me, Dependants cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch to me, Brokers borrow for me, Vſurers lend me, Flatterers extol <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, luſty Laſſes aduance me, ſtoope to me, and hang about my necke like goodly Iewels, as they proue. But now I a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled vnder the wheele of Chance, all is turned topſie turney, <hi>Qui nuper albus cram, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>unc ſum con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rarius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lbo.</hi> Gallants in their Paſquill humours begin to gird at me. <hi>Curia p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>peribu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> eſt.</hi> Lawyers haue no feeling of my caſe: Tradeſmen will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ue
<pb facs="tcp:10696:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>no commerce with me; Dependants hang downe their heads as if they were going to hanging: Brokers become boiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous: Vſurers miſuſe me. Thus am I vſed for vſing them: thus am I deceiued for truſting them: thus am I deſpiſed for imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing them: thus am I become a caſtaway for caſting away my money amongſt them. Now there is no wealth left, they are all loſt, now my gold is flowne they are all fled, and now am I in want, they are all vaniſhed like vnto an empty cloude. Oh that you would but ſend ſome Reuenge vpon ſome of them, that others of my rancke, ſeeing ſome of their fals, may ſhun the like places, and amend their follies, and they themſelues relent, and haue their remorſeles hearts turned: if out of their bellies, honeſtye and vpright dealing ſhould haue no great loſſe.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The Spendall.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Sergeant attends on him.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Sergeant.</note>VVOuld all our Luſty-Guts would looke in at this looking glaſſe. He was as well rigg'd a Pinnace, as ſome that make a greater ſhew, and as well mann'd till the boiſterous blaſts of his owne affections ſplitted him vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the rocks of Riot. He was as louely as <hi>Laeander,</hi> before he caſt himſelfe into the Sea of ſenſuality, and might in time haue proued a <hi>Co-adiutor</hi> of his countries weale, had hée cloſed his cares at the inueigling of <hi>Sea-Lures,</hi> and ſhut his mouth when <hi>Circe</hi> preferred him the cup to quaffe, which turned him to a beaſt, or more wretched then a beaſt in theſe daies, A beggar. But what is he that attendeth him ſo cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the gowne.</p>
               <p>It ſéemeth (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) that you neither truſt nor are truſted:<note place="margin">The opinion of the Ser. geant.</note> Either you haue ſtood in no need of money, or you want credit to borrow: or if you haue borrowed, you pay ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to prounſe, and appointment; elſe he would haue ben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo bold as to haue clapped you vpon the ſhoulder, and ben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> better acquainted with you, though you cared not greatly for his acquaintance, if euer you came into the precincts of his Iuriſdiction: He is an Officer, whoſe office I diſallow not,
<pb facs="tcp:10696:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>but diſlike ſome of his fratrernitie in their extreame execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of their duties, which will fawne like <hi>Spaniels,</hi> on ſuch as bribe them, and will be inquiſitiue after them. where they are ſure they are not: But mercileſſe <hi>Furies</hi> to haunt out poore men, which are diſable to fee, and féed them with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and that which ſheweth them to be no Chriſtians on the Sabboath day: He is at the beſt but a decayed <hi>Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> or vnthrifty <hi>Occupier,</hi> which how diſſolutely or baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſoeuer he liued before, is good inough is be as he is, The quartaine Feuer to a <hi>Spendall:</hi> the Plague to had <hi>Pay-mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters:</hi> the <hi>Vſurers</hi> foiſting hound: a neceſſary naile in the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Common wealth to claw men by the poles.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>A Sergeant</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The countrey Client paſſeth along.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The countrey Client.</note>HE hath neuer a <hi>Petition</hi> to preferre, vnleſſe againſt ſuch as are wiſe enough to keepe their money, while they haue it, and pay duly where they owe. But ſtay, what is he that noddeth next? if my eye-fight faile nie not, a ſhort cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pulent fellow with a full face, and foule hands, couered like a Capeaſe all with leather, backt with a broad dagger, a long ſword which handleth the forepart of his ſlops very rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly: now is his browne bonnet whipt betweene his legs, and he ſtands groping for his <hi>Petition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This man (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) you ſee ſo plainly attired, is quite tired with following the law:<note place="margin">The opinion of the country Client.</note> who though he ſeeme ſo plaine, hath as many crooked conditions in his Coſtrell, as a ſlight of your fineſt faſhion mongers. If he be Church war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, the Pariſhoner he maligneth, is ſummoned vpon ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if he giue but a well looking Laſſe a good morrow, or good night. If he be Conſtable, all the Alewines are vndone: If his neighbour treſpaſſe againſt him, he will neuer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue him. He will worſhip any man for his commodity, but where he neither feareth nor hopeth, He is haile fellow, well met. Cocknies map laugh at him, as he laggeth along the
<pb facs="tcp:10696:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>pauements, and Guls giggle when he paſſeth by their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per perſonages: but if he could yet vantage he would make them pay for the whole dozen: Let him alone, whether his haue his Oates, Peaſe, or Beanes, yet he wanteth no fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hes. Lend an ears to his Petition, if it be truly ſpeld, hée will coniure ſomebody.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The contrey-Clyents Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition.</note>Long haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iued, and grieued to ſee ſo many citizens be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Bankrouts, when Lawyers flouriſh, and breath and braule to the vtter ruine and vndoing of ſuch pooremen as my ſelfe, who hauing an homely wife and children at home, an compelled to come in <hi>Coram</hi> to this moſt deare Cittie, where I lie at exceeding charges, following the Law, which I faiue would flie: But neceſſity hath no Law, for hauing no fees, I may find a Lawyer (adding but a Maiſter to it) who hath either no Law in his budget, or no conſcience in his breaſt. So my caſe hath bene conſidered, and hung ſo long in Weſtminſter hall, as my fathers Bowcaſe in mine owne hall, euer ſince he died, and left certaine lands to be parted amongſt his ſonnes, who, becauſe we could not deuide them according to euery one of our contents, were contented to crouch to certaine Lawyers, who conceiuing the controuerſie, and perceiuing vs at ſuch variance, like our friends and welwillers promiſed to take <hi>our parts:</hi> and indeed not to belie them, they haue bene as good as their promiſes, and haue taken <hi>our parts,</hi> and not left vs an hole, or part to thruſt our heads into. And now we lacke <hi>vnde:</hi> they come ouer vs with a <hi>Quare,</hi> which put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs into a <hi>Quandary,</hi> to be ſent farre with neuer a farthing. It were ingratitude not to requite our welwillers and <hi>parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> or at leaſt, to wiſh wel vnto them that we cannot requite. My Petition therfore is, that you would conferre an hundreth marks or two vpon ſuch Pillers, or rather Caterpillers, I mean ſuch markes, as may marke them, to make others marke and beware of them. But for thoſe rare, admirable, miraculous, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, conſcionable, graue deciders, which weigh the matter more then the money, preferre the Commonweale, more then their owne priuate wealth: pleade for the poore, as well
<pb facs="tcp:10696:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>as Nobles: permit the not <hi>guiltie,</hi> ouerthrow the <hi>guiltie;</hi> I pray that they may liue many merry and Hillarie termes, for the good of their countrey, and profit of themſelues, and their poſteritie.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>The countrey Client.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Hoſtler followeth him.</head>
               <p>SUre, ſaid I, this Petition was neuer of his owne making, it is pincked ſo Pedantically, cut vpon fuſtian Phraſes,<note place="margin">The Hoſtler</note> and bound about with <hi>Mocke-adoes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Reſolue your ſelfe (anſwered <hi>Opinion</hi>) your countriman in many places is ſo metamorphoſed in maners now a daies, and quaint tearmes, that you ſhall hardly diſtinguiſh <hi>Pan</hi> from <hi>Apollo,</hi> but by the habit, and ſo captious in words, that you can vtter no word that he will not equinocate, if the <hi>Idiome</hi> will beare it. He ſpeaketh ſo ambignouſly, that if his ſpeech be conſtrued one way, he knoweth how to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret it after another ſignification, &amp; is not the man you take him, for if you take him for a plaute, ſilly,<note place="margin">The Hoſtler leadeth the countrey Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him.</note> honeſt man at all times, and in euery reſpect. You haue ſaid enough of him, but I pray you what is he for a man that doth follow him, he hath a ſticke in his hand, which he whiſketh as he leadeth the horſe by the bridie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The opinion of a kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ue Hoſtler<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note>He is as full of complement as his maiſter an Timekeeper: You are welcome Gentlemen, as all his eloquence, and that he ſheweth as well to a clowne, as a knight. At your entrance into his ſtable, he will be ſo obſequious and ſeruile, that he wil wipe your very horſes heeles. He ſtinketh line a Cure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>combe, and ſinelleth as ranke as Stale. He will giue your horſe a pecke of prouender (if it be your pleaſure) and ſteale halfe of it, if you eye him not narrowly. It night he filleth the racke with hay, but in the morning you ſhal not find an hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, though your horſe, nor any other by him ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>not a mouth full. If you abide any long ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and will hourely looke vnto pour beaſt, as it is beſt (for the eye of the maiſter maketh
<pb facs="tcp:10696:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>the horſe ſat he can take order for hes eating ouermuch, by greaſing his teeth with a tallow candle. He loueth brinde likely, and a drab if he be not married. He hath no yearely wages of his maiſter to maintaine him, but that which gueſts beſtow vpon him. To be briefe with him: at your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, if you giue him any thing in the chamber, when you make cleare with the houſe, he hath a ſwitch in one hand, and the bridle turned ouer the maine of your horſe, ſtanding in readineſſe, to hold your ſtirrop ſteadfaſtly, and did you heartily farewell: But if he finde you miſerable, your ſaddle gir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s are tied but ſlac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly, and if you like them not, you may mend them your ſelfe, and if you looke not before you leape<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you may perchance rue it. But he will hold your ſtirrop if you had him, he dare not deny it, it is a ſpeciall point of his profeſſion, but ſlac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ely, and with the head on the one ſide: and he will did you farewell (as his maiſter may heare) and bee hanged, (that he muttereth to himſelfe.) Though he be a knaue, yet he is a man of great calling (eſpecially when tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellers ride early on their iourney.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>An Hoſtler.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The old Seruingman paſſeth along.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ECce a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>em alterum,</hi> Behold a blew coate with neuer a badge on it,<note place="margin">The old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingman.</note> the crown<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of his head like a Franciſcans, <hi>Leno in facie,</hi> he looketh leane in the ſace, and lanhe in the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: All his apparrell looke as though they were caſt, a ſigne of a weake ſtomarke to beare ſtrong liquour. Looke how he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oth his hand as if he were in loue with it, and licketh the <hi>ſuperficies</hi> of the floore with his knees. Fie vpon it, how ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> he is in deliuering his Petition. Thoſe lowe legs, and kiſſing the hand (if he can cong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and lie to) would get him a ſeruice with ſome in the world, if he would ſerus three or foure yeares for no wages, he ſhould haue halfe a crowne at parting.</p>
               <p>Nay (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) he hath bene long enough in that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicament,
<pb facs="tcp:10696:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>and now can ſhew nought of his getting,<note place="margin">The opinion of the old Seruingman</note> vnleſſe children he dare not father. He was a pretty boy, an hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſtrippling, a proper man: péeuiſh in his childhood, proud in his youth, and prodigall in his beſt yeares: He hath wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted his protion in hope of preſerment: ſpent his ſubſtance, looking for aduancement; conſumed quite all, in expectation of ſome requitall. His greateſt felicitie was to court the chambermaids in ſome corner, &amp; his chiefe excerciſe to make his maiſters friends<note n="a" place="margin">Seruing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> dependants drunke. He was trained vp in ſome péece of a ioyners trade to make legs, and the beſt part of his <hi>Rhetoricke</hi> was, <hi>I forſooth,</hi> and <hi>No forſooth.</hi> The iniunctions that he was tied to, were to riſe at all houres, and to ride in all ſeaſons, eating that which was leſt, wearing that which was left, and marying oftentimes that which his maiſter leſt. Which ſheweth what he was, and is the<note n="b" place="margin">One that goeth before.</note> 
                  <hi>Anteambulo</hi> of a Gentle woman, the<note n="c" place="margin">One that followeth.</note> 
                  <hi>Subſequent</hi> of a Gentleman, the<note n="d" place="margin">One that ſitteth before.</note> 
                  <hi>Preſedent</hi> of a Portmantle, or a Cloake bagge.</p>
               <div type="petition">
                  <head>An old Seruingman, a young beggar.</head>
                  <p>Not without cauſe do I creepe to you with my Petition, praying either better fortune hereafter,<note place="margin">The old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingmans petition.</note> or reuenge vpon them that haue ſo ſlighted me off heretofore; who from my youth was brought vp in ſeruice, not in Gods ſeruice, but in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of man and woman, waiting for that which now I ſhall neuer get, becauſe I can waite no longer. So long as I was ſtrong, I was backt with ſomething: ſo long as I could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme all ſeruiceable duties, I wanted for no promiſes. But Time which turneth all things, hath turned me out of ſeruice, and Age which altereth all men, hath changed me from the top of Fauour to the toe of Contempt. Being now vſed like an old horſe, my cloake plucked of my backe, as his skin: Or an old dogge, kickt with diſdaine of euery vpſtart. Thus haue I bene ſerued for all my ſeruing: gained a daintie diſh, for car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo many daintie diſhes: got a goodly catch, for all my watching, and catching cold, for all my running<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and riding, tending, and tendering the welfare of thoſe, which conſider
<pb facs="tcp:10696:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>none, but themſelues. A man were better ſerue hogges, then ſome men, many wiues, moſt widdowes. Yet I would be loth to be miſconſtrued, or thought to cenſure any, but curious fooles; that none can pleaſe: ingratefull wretches, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a man hath ſpent the prime of his youth, hindered his fortunes, diſcharged the part of a faithfull ſteward, when his beautie fadeth, and ſtrength faileth, will thruſt him from them (becauſe he cannot performe his wonted charge) without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence or remorſe. For the world knoweth, and thouſands acknowledge, the munificent liberalitie of true Gentry, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended towards them, who by ſeruice haue climbed vp to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, their maiſters not enuying them, but lending their own hand and ſtrength to their aſcentions, whoſe childrens chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are bound to pray for them: when others, reſpected like my ſelfe, are forced to become humble Petitioners as I am, and are contrarily indebted. to them and theirs, if they do not degenerate from their Predeceſſors.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The old Seruingman.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The widdow with the old Seruingman.</head>
               <p>VVEll (thought I) though the fellow haue gained ſmal wages,<note place="margin">The Widdow</note> yet hath he great words (whereſoeuer he got them) and can ſay ſomething for himſelfe, though it auaile hun little. Let him be trauelling towards Beggers buſh, and thinke of his ſinnes in his maſters Buttery. But ſtay awhile he is in communication with a ſéeming well demeaned wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſomewhat ſtricken in yeares, yet well fauoured, and not paſt marriage.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The opinion of the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow.</note>She may do well you thinke (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) to make him a man, which made her a woman, when time was (or elſo there are hers.) But if ſhe be wiſe, ſhe will not hazard her good<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and her ſelfe. That ſhe hath ſhe is ſure of, and put the caſe ſhe walieth any thing for ſelfe, it will be leſſe care, then to haue another to laſh it out. The wilde coſt may proue a tame horſe, but a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lde youth is oftentimes a wilfull man.
<pb facs="tcp:10696:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Vince<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e conſuetudin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m dura eſt pugna.</hi> It is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e conflict to ſubdue cuſtome. She leadeth new a ſingle life (a ſingular life) ſhe hath her necke out of the yoke, ſhe n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> not thruſt it into it againt, vnleſſe ſhe luſt. If ſhe can kéepe her ſelfe as ſhe is, ſhe is well and a wealthy Widdow.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The maide gotten with childe commeth along.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The maide gotten with childe.</note>LEt them goe together on Gods name (ſaid I) but <hi>hei mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi,</hi> what a wofull ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ectacle is this? <hi>faciem pulchram,</hi> an amiable face, and louely looke: Prettie ſoule, why doth ſhe pouder thoſe freſh chéekes with ſalt teares? Alas, ſhe can ſcarce wallow, her belly is ſo full, yet ſhe ioggeth along<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though euery foote ſhe looketh to lie downe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Opinion of the maid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with child.</note>This is one (anſwered <hi>Opinion</hi>) whom Nature hath imbel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed with her rareſt ornaments, but fortune furniſhed with none of her riches<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> She was poore, therefore deſpaired of an huſband. Light of beliefe, therefore at this time heauy bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied. Another <hi>Dido </hi>to beléeue ſome wandering <hi>Aeneas:</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Aenone</hi> to credite ſome wandring <hi>Paris:</hi> another <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi> to truſt ſome ſwearing <hi>Demophon.</hi> He promiſed, and hath fulfilled (but I do not ſay his prounſe.) Becauſe he ſware he would neuer forſake her, ſhe ſuppoſed he would ſurely haue her: as though he which maketh no ſcruple to breake the ſeuenth Commandement, will make any conſcience to kéepe the third. The apples were faire the tree c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ly, and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell at hand made her fall to them, which procured her fail, and that fall was the cauſe of this ſwelling.</p>
               <div type="petition">
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Petition of the maid with childe.</note>If euer any might proffer a Petition for right, or reuenge. I haue as great reaſon as any, Being a pure and vntoucht vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, voted to Veſta, and deuoted to Chaſtity, till a venerous villaine with daily aſſaults and nightly trecheries, neuer left battering the weake bulwarke of my heart with piercing words, vowes, oaths, &amp; proteſtations, darted from his ſmooth tongue, till he had ſurpriſed me. Hearing him oftentimes ſweare, ſeeing him teare his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aire nay, which is more ſtrange
<pb facs="tcp:10696:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>for a man, weepe in moſt ſeeming ſadneſſe, kiſſe my hand with foure and trembling, and voluntarily proffer, and performe much ſeru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>de, which I neither deſired nor deſerued. Being guilt leſſe of effecting deceit, was free from ſuſpecting: fearing to breake an oath, or violate a vow, truſted that he had bene poſſeſſed with the like feare, (as he was not) at laſt condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Which ſo ſoone as he had accompliſhed, he left me: It is no glory to deceiue a maide, no manhood to ouerthrow the weaker veſſell. Yet being outwardly garniſhed with the gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ous workmanſhip of Art and Nature, what labour will not ſome men take to attaine this veſſell? what watchings will they not vndergoe? what wealth will they not waſt to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe it? And when they haue gotten it, how do they eſteeme it? euen a toy to be plaid with for a time, and after too. For ſo ſoone as they eye another deuice, they caſt away the old, and neuer are in quiet till they are fingering the new, Fie vpon ſuch, they are like warriours of old time, which would ſpend much coſt, and labour to ſubdue a citie, and when they had brought it into ſubiection, they would inſtantly leaue it, and ſo march to another, &amp;c. Or like the fantaſticall fellowes of our time, which cannot keepe long in one cut, but euery foot haue a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ing at a new faſhion: but all not ſo, and I would there were ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er that are ſo.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The maide with childe.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Parriter rideth after the maide with childe.</head>
               <p>I Sée <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ce off, riding as it were to this maide, he will not be here very ſoone,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>er</note> he is ſo ill horſed. In the meane t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e I will acquaint you with a ieſt not vnfit to be inſerted in this place. There was a prettie maide which in her time had many ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ters the firſt whereof was verie vrgent to haue his delights with her as I heard a crooked legd knaue terme it: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e being a tender hearted thing, as it ſeemed this was, after a little willing waywardneſſe was wonne, and loſt
<pb facs="tcp:10696:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>together. After he had forſaken her, a ſecond came, and ſet lied her in like manner: then a third, and after a fourth, (birds of a feather, they flew all after the foremoſt.) Being thus handled, ſhe began to ware warie, and forſwore ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting. In this reſolution a fifth came vnto her, whoſe condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was to trie all, and if they did ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, he would come no more there. This Gentleman wooing the foreſaid ſuppoſed maide, ſet his wit and wealth vpon the tenters, to obtaine his purpoſe, but nothing could preua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e. She rayled moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregiouſly againſt his diſhoneſt and vniuſt requeſt, and ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the motion: which pleaſed him very weſt though he ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med diſcontented) and married her. The ſecond night they lay together, he began to ſpeake thus vnto her: Thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt (ſwéet heart) how earneſt I was to lie with thée before I might lawfully; and I proteſt, if thou hadſt ſuffered me, we had neuer bene matried together. The wife, whether ſhe was halfe a ſléepe, or ouer ioyed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> had the heart of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Owle (which they ſay cauſeth women to reuea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets) laide to her left pappe,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> anſwered him thus. Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> huſband, I was wiſe enough for that, I tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w: for three or foure had ſerued me ſo before I euer beheld your face. This tale I thought méete to ſet downe in this place, that if any maide chance to reade ouer this booke, ſhe might take been how ſhe diſhoner her ſeife with any, whether ſhe ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> marrieth not, for it will breed future <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alouſie though ſhe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer after deſerue it. But now the horſeman is alighted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> readeth ſomething to the maide gotten with childe,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ter crueth a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſe. &amp;c.</note> what he is I cannot certainly ſay, but I do not like his looks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that péece of parchment in his hand.</p>
               <p>I will not runne (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) into any particulars with him,<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> he is better knowne in the countrey then in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e And whoſoeuer are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tus, or in cuts as I may ſpeake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with him, know him to be in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>eſt man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> knaue.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ter</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10696:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>The reiected louer walketh along.</head>
               <p>LEt him returne that anſwer to the Court, and ſée if they can haue an action of ſlander againſt you,<note place="margin">The Louer.</note> and obſerue him now that commeth next with his Petition, ſo trimly tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ked vp: not a haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iſſe with him, vnleſſe that which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the one doe of his ſhoulder, what a your blinde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e which polled him laſt. Come a little nearer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> now, he can make his old cloake ſerue the turne, in the laſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tion ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly corrected and augmented, laced and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed. He hath a ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>enecke, which God hateth, and a ſtrait <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which no faithfull drunkarde an indure, for if he had what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ing, he would not leaue if worth a botton: but the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of his b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aches, ſure he had an honeſt Tayler, elſe he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> might haue taken as much from both the out does next his knées as would haue made him two ends of a wallet, which now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e very like a paire of Smiths bellowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng with the ſmalleſt ends <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>wards. A ſweet youth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, for he hath two Roſes on his ſhoes to qualliſie the ſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> if he haue no ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ckes, or one would make a Pope of him, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his toe. But why doth he ſigh ſo déepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ly?</p>
               <p>This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llow is no feele, although he be none of the wiſeſt: he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es no more for money (if he haue it) ſo he may pleaſe his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">The deſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Louer.</note> then for ſuch mettall as ſerues onely for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>: He can fit his humour to euery eſtate. If he be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>g Sch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llers he hath <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> at his fingers ends and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>y ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe ſmels of <hi>Cicero.</hi> He can ſhew wit in quicks of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>try, and reading in diſputations of Philoſophy. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Courtiers he can braue it out as well as the reſt, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, with moſt louing and amorous pratile: with them he is in his <hi>Q.</hi> and keepes the old text, <hi>Bonum eſt nobis eſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ic.</hi> But their company ſo beſots him, that he forgetteth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yſſes</hi> to ſtay his cares, and therefore the <hi>Syrens</hi> put him to ſhip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cke. He carrieth not the Antidote of <hi>Caueat Emp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or,</hi> againſt the alluting baites of their beautie, and therefore Folly (for the moſt part) is his next hauen.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10696:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>He remembers not, that the eyes of wicked women are ſnares, and their worde charmes, that their deceipt is much, their deſires more, and their couetonſneſſe moſt;<note place="margin">The Louer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Petition.</note> which the more it drinkes the more thirſty it is: their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences like a Pomice ſtone, light, and full of holes: whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ones are for lucre, whoſe hearts are light on his perſon, and whoſe hands are heauy on his purſe. If he hit vpon a Curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zan that is a little ioy, though ſhe be altogether vnchaſt, his delight is to be on her lappe: there he lies at racke and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, &amp; thinkes there are no more maids then <hi>Malkin.</hi> There he ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iteth like <hi>Sardanapalus,</hi> dallying with the ſla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, till he burn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the fire. So as in the end, comming home by wée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Croſſe, he buyeth repentance with too deare a price, and becommeth at laſt, A ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd, deſpiſed, and reiected Louer.</p>
               <div type="petition">
                  <p>Being worne with griefe, and waſted with diſcontent, I am conſtrained to ſeeke remedy and ſome eaſe to my minde, which you may affoord by doing reuenge vpon an inconſtant Female, who plighted her faith to me, &amp; priuatly proclaimed me the ſole Lord of her Microcoſm: but before I was inſtalled I was foreſtalled by the vndermining perſwaſions of a treche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous vſurper, who with his ſeruile curteſies hath inſinuated himſelf into my dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Who would truſt the wind? A wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans words: who would relie vpon a broken reed? a womans oath. They ſigh for them that hate them, and laugh at moſt that loue them. They will haue ſome that will not, and will haue few that would faine. Some feeling of their fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly had he, which when he beheld his neighbors wife <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ang <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er ſelfe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon one of the trees in her husbands orchyar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, req<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tled a graft of the ſame tree, to ſee if it would beare any more or the like fruite. And no light burthen did that paſſenger account his wife, who, when the reſt in the ſhip were willed to caſt all the bagge and baggage<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which no ſurcharge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, ouer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, was moſt willing to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uity his wife into the Sea. Some <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hew then learning or rather ignorance, may make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>nes of <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>comions</hi> in then behalfes, and get per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aps a <hi>Iudas</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ile, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a flay with a Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le for their labours. For he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10696:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>or read any thing at all of this <hi>Common place,</hi> ſhall finde for one <hi>Veſta,</hi> many vitious; for one <hi>Diana,</hi> many darlings; for one <hi>Lucrece,</hi> many laſciuious: did neuer any but <hi>Semeramis</hi> lie with her owne ſonne? Did neuer any but <hi>Mir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ha</hi> twine with her owne father? Did neuer any but <hi>Biblis</hi> dote vpon her own brother? Did neuer any miſtreſſe but <hi>Ioſephus</hi> tempt her houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould ſeruants? One is no number, I would there were no number of theſe ones, vpon which if you fall, you will bee</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The forlorne Louer.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The countrey Schoolemaiſter commeth to the Louer.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter.</note>IT is happy you are ſo ſhort, elſe we had b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne wearied with your louely Petition. Me thinkes yonder is one that crin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to him: all his apparell is not woorth one Marke, yet he hath a hat on his head of the Spaniſh blocke: put the blocke and his head together and ſée what they ſpell. Well done honeſt <hi>genus</hi> and <hi>ſpecies</hi> (for thou ſéemeſt inclining as it were, that way by thy habite, and pen and inkchorne) reade a pée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of <hi>Ouid de Remedio amoris</hi> to him, for though he raile vnreaſonably againſt women, yet I am perſwaded he doth chaſtiſe them, <hi>non quod odio habet, ſed quod amat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Opinion of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſtes.</note>
                  <hi>Atque hoc humanum eſt</hi> (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) This man you ſée which maketh ſuch action with his hands, as he talketh with the <hi>Louer,</hi> is one that kéepeth a foule ioyle in the Chancell or Belfrée of a Church. He is a moſt horrible Tyrant ouer little children, and makes their bréeches quauer with the ſhake of his Scepter, <hi>alias</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Rod. He getteth his liuing, <hi>non perſe,</hi> but for the moſt part, <hi>per accidens.</hi> Yet he can teach <hi>Grammer</hi> and <hi>Aeſops Fables,</hi> for he hath them both in print, tranſlated <hi>verbum de verbo.</hi> Howſoeuer ſchollers do eſtéem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of him, ignorant Hobnailes hold him for a rar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Scholler, for he will ſpeake Latine amongſt them <hi>extrumpere,</hi> and ſcan verſes at his fingers ends. He is a man of ſharpe learing, which pea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th hard words: he worketh by Rule, like a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter,
<pb facs="tcp:10696:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>and can caſt a figure, as if he were a coniurer. He is very curious, and ſtandeth much a vpon points, he may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tly be coupled with the <hi>Louer.</hi> For either he is enamoured of his own good parts, or in loue with the waiting maid, if he tabled in a Gentleman houſe, &amp; ſometimes winneth her good will, but neuer can get her friends conſent. To be brief with him, as her in with his infants, a word and a blow: Hee is the outſide of a Sohollee, an imperious commander ouer boyes and wenches, the head maiſter of the Péepe taile trade</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>A Pedant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The old woman married to a yong man commeth next.</head>
               <p>SO let them all walke <hi>Newgate faſhion, two by two: Who is that which hobleth next?</hi> Chriſt bleſſe the woman:<note place="margin">The old wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man married to a young man.</note> So, wipe your mouth with your Handkerchiefe after your coughing and ſpitting. Her forehead is wrinckled like a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per lanthorne, which boyes make: with two thinne chéekes, like two waſht trenchers, betweene which, her noſe ſéemeth like the ſocket, wherein the ſnot ſtands like a péece of a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Candle. Her mouth like a Caue with two clap doores, to wit, her two lips, without a bolt, that is without a tooth, containing a <hi>Pilgrime,</hi> a wandring tongue, which mouth (like a Caue) ſtandeth like a Caue betweene two ſharpe pointed hils, whoſe tops do almoſt touch one another, her Noſe and her Chinne.</p>
               <p>Mocke <hi>Age</hi> (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) and ſee how you will thriue. This toothleſſe, ſapleſſe, ſenceleſſe <hi>Beldam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The opinion of the old woman mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to the yong man.</note> was wife to an honeſt ſubſtantiall man, who during his youth endured much labour in gathering riches to maintaine himſelfe in yeares; and her, if ſhe ſhould be <hi>ſuperſtes,</hi> or out liue him, as ſhe hath. So ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e had all he left (which was ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cient) at her owne di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſing, who was had enough diſpoſed as it ſeemed: For as ſoone as her huſband was ſurely buried, ſhe was all on the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te, ſhe could not he alone. An huſband was all her care, and many graue men ſhe had choice of, but ſhe gaue ſmall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement
<pb facs="tcp:10696:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>to any of their haire, ſhe had rather haue the legge of a Larke, then the body of a Rite: yet the feathers hang in her Maw, which ſhe cannot digeſt nor vomite, till death lance her throate with his razor. Her Petition will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neale all, for women cannot kéepe their owne ſecrets. Onely this, ſhe is, as it were<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a buſh of thornes thruſt to the hinder parts of a Colt. A verie old woman married to a young man.</p>
               <div type="petition">
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Petition of the old wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man married to the yong man.</note>Though I might haue bene better aduiſed by my friends, forewarning (I confeſſe) yet ſince I am in the like pickle as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and haue had no leſſe misfortune then they, I may wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my woes, and cannot chuſe but put vp my Petition with theirs. Who as it is well knowne, was wealthy, and therefore ſoone wonne: an old woman, and therefore ſooneſt wronged by a beggerly varlet: who at my firſt view ſeemed ſo ciuilly behaued, as none could miſlike him: ſo well proportioned, as I could not chuſe but like him eſpecially hauing an honeſt vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, as he profeſſed, and was well deſcended though a yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger brother, which had his portion to take, as he brought me Certificate. But now I perceiue theſe were but trickes to catch Dotterils. His ſmooth tongue being his onely friend, the ſleight and craft of his hands, his onely <hi>handie-craft,</hi> his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion his onely <hi>portion,</hi> which he had to take. For after wee were married he ſoothed me vp, till I ſhewed him my ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and improuidently without any further trial, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it to his tuition: which when he had made ſure, he handled me moſt ingratefully: neuer touching my lips but with his fiſt, nor warming my ſides, but with an ell I vſed to meaſure cloath: alledging that if I exclaimed againſt him, he might ſafely ſweare, he did neuer beate me without meaſure. Hee would not be contented to waſte himſelfe and my riches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whores and royſters all the day: but at vnſeaſonable times, when I was in bed, ruſh into my houſe with his queans at his heels, &amp; rouſe me out of my reſt: make me to remake my bed with freſh ſheets for his Truls, &amp; would leape in amongſt them, I being compelled to hold the candle to the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ll,
<pb facs="tcp:10696:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>whileſt he did his deeds of darkeneſſe: Thus did he vſe me, till I complained to Authoritie which relieued me, reuiled and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded him my houſe and company. Then did he depart like a Sheepe-biter, retiring himſelfe into a priuate chamber, caſt off his guilded Rapier, ſpruce leather Boots, and Spurres, got him a Cloake without laces, made a Dublet with a falling choller, wore Gloues of ſixepence a paire on his hands: no points on his Breeches, but at the waſtband: a paire of ſad coloured ſtoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, tied vp ſtraight with Garters no broader then an Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers belt, and his Shooe-latches bound together with ruſſet Inckle: frequented Sermons, ſent me moſt paſſionate letters, that he had renounced Roiſters, abjured whores, ſetled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>himſelfe to a ſtayed and religious courſe, and that he ſhamed to appeare in the place I dwelled, he had ſo wronged me and himſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But if I would go into the country with him, he would purchace ſome conuenient place, where he might liue ſolitarie from all company, but my ſelfe, and ſeruants. His fained re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance ſeemed ſo heartie, and his flattering lines wrought ſo with me, that we became attoned, made money of all, and went together, and for three or foure dayes he vſed me kindly and lay very quietly with me in the nights, but the fiftth night (being farre from my friends) when I was faſt aſleepe, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer dreamed of any ſuch matter, ſtole all I had, &amp; ranne away. what way I cannot heare, or learne any tidings.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The old woman married with the yong man.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Clarke commeth to the old woman.</head>
               <p>THis is the end of liquorice, when a woman hath neuer a tooth in her head to chaw it.<note place="margin">The Clar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</note> At a glimpſe I ſee a young man with her. Hath ſhe not yet abandoned the company of men without beards? If hee be not the man ſhe ſpoke ſo much of, what is he?</p>
               <p>He is one that you ſhall ſeldome ſee without cleane linnen,<note place="margin">The opinion of a Cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e.</note> he weareth good cloathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and can write a legible hand: hee
<pb facs="tcp:10696:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath a little learning, and will ſhew it all if you conferre with him: when he rideth abroad with his maſter, hée car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth two hats, and walketh with a caſe of Rapiers, one by his ſide, the other in his hand, his maſters and his owne. At dinner or ſupper, either at home or elſewhere, he waiteth at his maſters elbowe with a trencher at his backe, yet hée can reach a cleane voider to any of the table, if he take a liking to the peece he hath on his foule trencher, he marrieth his maſters daughter ſometimes, which hee hath ſtolne away, (God a mercie <hi>Oportunitie.</hi>) He can make bonds and obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to pleaſure the pariſh, if their Vicar haue not ſo much Latine, and indite a loue letter for himſelfe or his fellowes: if any miſdemeanour be committed neare him, when com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint is made thereof, he writeth warrants to apprehend the offendors. He is a Iuſtices Clarke, which may warrant this old woman for getting her huſband or her goods againe, though ſhe pray, and pay neuer ſo many warrants.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The yong woman commeth married to an old man.</head>
               <p>ANother paſſeth on paſſing portly, a ſwéete woman, ſhe ſmelleth hither:<note place="margin">The young woman.</note> and a rolling eye ſhe hath, it turneth with a trice on both ſides: a faire haire, if it be her owne: a rare face if it be not painted: a white ſkinne, if it be not pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered: a full breaſt, if it be not bolſtered: a ſtraite backe, if it be not helped: a ſlender waſte, if it be not pinched: a likely legge if it be not lined: a pretty foote-if it be not in the Shoomakers ſtockes: a faire, rare, ſweete, méete body, if it be not diſhoneſt.</p>
               <p>Your ſuppoſes poſe me (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) neither can I ſay or gaineſay.<note place="margin">The opinion of the young woman mari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed to the old Man.</note> Nature in beautie is better then Art; yet Art in ſhew ſurpaſſeth Nature. She is proudly attired, yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance humbly minded: loftily aduanced, yet it may be low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſcended: vildly ſuſpected, yet peraduenture vertuouſly addicted. The world now adaies is round with ſuch as ſhee
<pb facs="tcp:10696:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>is, and too raſh in their cenſures: condemning ſuch as are innocent, and quitting many that are culpable: but that which is paſt mending is paſt medling withall. Therefore leaue it, and looke vpon this luſtre: faire ſhe is and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuours: riches ſhe enioyes, yet hath no great ioy of riches: married ſhe is, yet I make queſtion, whether ſhe bee a maide or no, being a young woman married to a verie olde iealous man.</p>
               <div type="petition">
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Petition of the young Woman mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the old Man.</note>My requeſts are not vnreaſonable, nor voide of good cauſe, being a woman of tender age, as your eyes may witneſſe, and of a vexed ſpirit, as theſe lines will manifeſt: that would chuſe rather to be laide in my graue then on my bed; feede of the wormes, then eate with ſuch a worme-eaten old iealous husband as I doe: whoſe age I doe reuerence, and find fault with no deformitie, which time hath thruſt vpon him, but with his cauſleſſe ſuſpitions, and immerited miſtruſts of me. For did he hemme more then a towne of Taylers, or hawke oftner then a countrey of Faulkners, I could endure it I am ſo enured thereunto: were the parts of his body neuer ſo <hi>nanſeas</hi> &amp; deteſtable, I could away with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo his reaſon were ſound and ſauory: but his wiſdome (like his eyes) is ſunke into his head, too farre for hereafter appearing: his will ſtronger then his breath: his vnderſtanding feebler then his fingers: and his iudgement corrupter then his body.<note place="margin">The praiſe of ſome olde Men.</note> It is an admiration to ſee the difference of ſome of his yeares, how directly they will talke, what maieſtie is in their lookes, what wiſedome in their diſcourſe? Not a word without his weight, not a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence without good ſence: not a deed vnleſſe abſolutely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. They will blame nothing that is not blame worthie, nor condemne any without aſſured reaſon. But my <hi>Zelotipus</hi> raileth without reaſon, knocks his ſtaffe againſt the ſtones, blames me without offence. On that ſome good Fortune would therefore cure me of this care, and ſalue me of this ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: For neuer ſhall I reape dayes reſt, nights content, houres quiet, minutes mirth, ſo long as I haue this impoſtume in my head, this pinne and webbe in mine eye, this canker in my
<pb facs="tcp:10696:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>noſe, this ſcabbe on my lippe, this iealous old huſband.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The young woman married with a very old iealous man.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>Now I heare this Petition, it bringeth into my minde a merry conceit. There was a very old man, which married a maide, who méeting a friend of his, did importune him to know what the people ſpake of his marriage. Who made him this anſwer: There was a poore man which had but one pec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e of corne to grinde, and would needs build a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ill to grinde it, and when he had ground his corne, the mill ſtood emptie, ſo that afterwards all the neighbours came to grind their grifts there. This I inferre, not to defame any, but to ſhew how ready the world is to ſpeake the worſt.</p>
                  <p>Whatſoeuer you ſay (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) vnequall marriages doe marre ages, and ſuch made matches as theſe, proue but mad matches, yet of the two, I hold it more conuient that old <hi>Tithon</hi> ſhould haue a freſh <hi>Amora,</hi> then an aged wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to be linked in matrimony with a beardleſſe boy.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Cuckold paſſeth along.</head>
               <p>SVffient for this theame, another doth appeare or rather péere.<note place="margin">The Cuckold</note> heauens ſecure my ſences, if I be not diſtracted, he is a <hi>Proteus,</hi> a <hi>Camelion,</hi> an <hi>Omnigatherum,</hi> God make him an honeſt man, for I would be loath to make any one ſuch a one as he is.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Opinion of a Cuckold</note>He will trouble me paint him, (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) I know not what coulours to lay vpon his face, for ſometimes he is of a ſanguine complexion, ſometimes he looketh pale, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times tawny, or <hi>Moritawny,</hi> like <hi>Tobacco.</hi> Neither can I tell how to frame him, for he is ſometimes tall, ſometimes lowe, ſometimes groſſe, ſometimes gracile. Nor expreſly ſay what vocation he is of, for ſometimes he is a Citizen, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a Farmer ſometimes a Lawyer, ſometimes a Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, &amp;c. He hath a proper woman to his wife, yet common, he toyleth to maintaine other mens labours, yet he reapeth that which he neuer wrought for, he waſteth all the corne in his owne hatches on other mens Barnes, yet he keepeth that which he neuer got, But to draw you out of this Laborinth
<pb facs="tcp:10696:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>with one line, <hi>Cornu ferit ille,</hi> If he haue not Cornes on his Toes, he hath Hornes on his Head. He is his wiues foole amongſt her copeſmates, wanton wenches paſtime amongſt themſelnes, and wagges game to play at with two fingers.</p>
               <div type="petition">
                  <head>A Cuckold.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Cuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olds Petition.</note>Loath I am to bewray my griefes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> you, did not the loathing of the life I lead egge mee againſt my nature to wiſh that I would not: I haue many yeares beene bound in a bond, which hath vndone mee, yoaked with a curtall which hath plaide me many Iades trickes, a wanton wayward wel fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red wife: who falſifying her faith and breaking the bondes ſhe ſealed moſt ſolem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nely before a congregation, doth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that which ſhame ſylenceth me for vttering. I dare not meete her, ſhe keepes ſuch couragious company I cannot content her any way, ſhe hath outwardly what ſhe likes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly: and what ſhe thruſtes away with one finger, ſhe pulles againe with both her hands: when I fawne on her, ſhe will be froward: If I be but a little abſent, ſhe wiſhes my preſence. Her thoughts are like Babyes fancies, that will, and will not. My deedes cannot ſuffice her, for ſhe is a woman. My ſpeech cannot pleaſe her ſhe is ſo captious, nor my lookes like her, ſhe is ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>curious. None feele the rages of deſeaſes, but they which haue them. None ſo truly knovv the torments of hell, as they which feele them? Nor any feeleth the torments, or knoweth the rages, that I doe, vnleſſe he liue in ſuch an hell, or haue the like deſeaſe, as I haue. Many, are haunted with hagges, but neuer any with ſuch an haggarde: They liue caute though not caſte: but my <hi>Venus</hi> lyeth ſo viſibly in her Net<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes, that not only Gods eyes, but mens behold her. Yet fayne would I reforme her, but neither faire meanes can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade her, not fowle ſcarre her. If I indeauour with good counſell to diſſawde her from her former follies, her anſwer is, I preach too learnedly for her to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>fy by me. If I plead plainely with her, then at the next word, I am Sir Ionu Lacklatine: If I can collect ſome witty ſaying fit for my purpoſe, that will toucho her to the quicke, then ſhe ſaith,
<pb facs="tcp:10696:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>I am all wit, or a wit all: If I threaten her, ſhe hath enough to ſhield her: If I meation but a bill of diuorcement, it is her only deſire: If I keepe her ſhort of money, ſhee makes deuilliſh oathes and vowes that ſhee will haue Money, or ſome body ſhal pay for it: if I for quietnes ſake ſhould lock her vp into her chamber, the next <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e I ſtirre abroad, I am arreſted for ſome debt of hers, which ſhee ranne into for ſuch a purpoſe.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>In me turba ruant luxur of a proci<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>In meâregnant, nullis prohibentibus, aulâ.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Neuer ſhall I enioy reſt, ſo long as ſhee and I breath toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Such therefore as haue not the ſame cauſes of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaintes as I haue, and yet liue not contented I wiſh their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes to bee, that they may be troubled with my paine and head-ache.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The Cuckold,</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The olde Souldier commeth along.</head>
               <p>BUt ſtay, heeres an other limpeth a long: pitty a mec, an <hi>Hetaroclite,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The old Souldier.</note> hee lacketh an hande. There are ſcarres on his face, would ſcarre a tumorous body to behold: he looketh grauely, as though he had not long to liue, and leaneth vpon his trunchion, as if his body were about to fall away: come alongſt luſtily, and half not before thy freinds. Sure hee is a man of worth for hee hath his hangers on.</p>
               <p>Your ieſts (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) are too tart, and your merry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ouer much vpon ſo monefull a <hi>Man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Opinion of the old Souldier.</note> which deſecueth to be pittyed, rather then to be plaide vpon, and meriteth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leife more then mocking. He hath borne Armes, howſoeuer now hee be diſarmed: he hath had a ſword to ſticke by him, though now he hath no other weapon then a ſticke in his hand: he hath loſt his limmes but not in ſome druncken fray, and got thoſe <hi>Cycatrices,</hi> but not in the defence of any <hi>Cocatrices:</hi> He hath fought againſt the walles of the enemy but neuer fought againſt any for the wall, as he walked in the ſtreete. He will not ſtab be for the lye, and yet he will
<pb facs="tcp:10696:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>not take the lye in his Countries diſgrace. Hee is none of your ſwaſhing Captaines, that vſurpe the title, when they neuer fought vnder any coulours but <hi>Venus-es:</hi> and they will dye rather then they will flye from her coulours. Neuer handled peece, vnleſſe of meat, bread &amp;c. Neuer diſcharged ſhot vnles in a Tauerne where they met with too hot ſhots ſometimes for their diſcharging. Neither is he any of your counterfet <hi>Duello's,</hi> diſcourſing of battailes they neuer came neare, telling of monſters they neuer beheld, vnles in a pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted cloath: ſwearing they were hurt in the defence of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity againſt <hi>Mahomotiſtes,</hi> when if they were wounded, it was at Groyne at farthect. He is no Triton of his owne praiſes: nor Chronologer of his olde exploites, he is an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Coward in wrangling brawles, a more Crauen in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt conflictes, a very Pigmey in paltrey frayes: but in a iuſt cauſe as valorous as Pector, and as puiſſant as <hi>Hercules,</hi> a true, faithfull and religious Souldier.</p>
               <div type="petition">
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Petition of the old Souldier.</note>My humble ſute is for better Fortune, for men are now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo ingratefull and hard hearted, that they doe not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider thoſe which haue bene their friends, nor reward ſuch as when neede ſerued, warded them from imminent diſtreſſes: the times paſt no man thinkes vpon: the time to come few dreame of: but all are for the time preſent. A Souldier hath helped them, and now God helpe Souldiers, for not many will: a ſouldier may helpe them, and then may helpe himſelfe, and then they will helpe him alſo: but now a Souldier doth them no good, and therefore they will doe him as little. They liue in peace, that beingeth plentie, and that pride: but pride may haue a fall, and peace and plentie their hoods turnd ouer their heads: which I neither wiſh nor pray for, but if they haue, <hi>Spernitur orator bonus, horridus wiles amatur.</hi> In the meane time, we, who haue wholly decaved our limbes, and impoueriſhed our eſtates in the warres, may ſhew our ſcarres to vncompaſſionate eyes, and receaue no further helpe then <hi>Chriſt helpe you,</hi> good words, <hi>would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> were able:</hi> good wiſhes for themſelues: when as the ſuperfluitie of one parre of their
<pb facs="tcp:10696:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhoe-ties would yeeld vs much confort: but I cannot, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will I goe about to condemne any abſolutely, the world is ſo peſtered with idle vagabonds, which vnder the name of Souldiers and forged paſports, haue ſo wronged ſome, that it withdraweth the hearts of moſt from conferring their bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolence vpon any: for I am perſwaded that no true borne ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit will deny ſome reliefe to a true Souldiers in his want. And Preheminence hath allowed them well, though it be ill e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough diſtributed in ſome places: the fault is not in the giuers, but of inferiours which are put in truſt to diſpoſe it. But the God of war hath ſo many <hi>Apoſtataes,</hi> that the true borne, fare the worſe for the illegitimate. This boone I therefore craue, that all the ranks of rogues, and runnagates, ſhrouding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the caſt-ſuites of Souldiers, might be rooted out, or ſent vpon a boone voyage to the new found Land, by which meanes Hens &amp; Capons may ſit at rooſt quietly in the night, and pecke about the garth all the day: ſhirts and other nape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie hang vpon hedges, till the Sun ſet, ſhops be kept ſhut, and windowes ſtand vvide open to let in aire, vvithout feare of Creepers, to the great comfort both of citie, and countrey.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The old Souldier.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Prentiſe cometh along.</head>
               <p>VVHen the Lion was old,<note place="margin">The Prentiſe</note> the Aſſe came and hicked him: and when a Souldier hath loſt his limmes, eueris coward will crow ouer him. I would ſay more in thy behalfe, and doe as much as I ſpeake, if I were able. But I amanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipated by the ſpeedie entrance of another, with his cloake clapt vnder his left Arme. A prettie youth, very decently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacelled, but he gorth very faſt, as if he went of an errant. What may he be.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The opinion of the Pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe</note>He may be a man (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi> if he line, an honeſt man man if he liue vpright. A ſound man, if he flie ſurfets, and whores: a thriuing man if he ſhunne riotous company: a rich men, if he be thriuing: a Sheriffe, if he be a rich man:
<pb facs="tcp:10696:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>An Alderman if he be a Sheriff: A Maior, if he be an Alderman: a Knight if he be a Maior: But yet he is a Prentiſe.</p>
               <div type="petition">
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Petition of the prentice</note>Diuers are the calamities of ſome of my rancke, and many the miſeries they are expoſed to, faring hardly, and labouring hardly: but ſuch as will we are Gold muſt get it, they which will wynne honour muſt wage with many aduentures: He which thincketh to proffie muſt caſhier the very thought of pleaſure, Ryding with care and running with paine: Sitting with prouidence, and lying with conſideration: Eating with frugality and drincking with moderation: Synce therefore honorable men muſt endeauour for Renowne: Learned men ſtudy for their knowledge: Richmen labour for their gaines: Tradeſmen trauell for their Sciences: All men, (which will liue like men in their age) labour like beaſts in their youth, vnles they haue Lands to truſt to: My meaning is not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parage learning, becauſe it is hard to attaine diſpraiſe honour, becauſe it is difficult to get: diſcourage Prentiſes, becauſe their beginnings are laborious: for I haue read that the baſe of <hi>Pernaſſus</hi> is full of briers, thornes, and thiſtles, but the toppe, plaine as heauen, &amp; ſmooth as the Moones face. I haue heard that the ſteppes which aſcend to honour, are like the ſtaires which mount to the hight of a <hi>Maze,</hi> many and endles. The dores conducting thervnto, infinite, and intricate, but the top like the toppe of <hi>Olimpus,</hi> and the roomes pleaſant, and ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, garniſhed with more then mortal obiects. And I know by Experience that the skill and ſecrecy of mechanicall Artes, are not got (like a looſe woman) at firſt ſight. Neither will yeild any great proffit at firſt labouring, any more then a barrein ground at the firſt ſowing, I doe not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Cauill with my calling, nor am penſiue for the paines I indure; but the originall of all my ſorrow is a Miſtreſſe ſo peeuiſh, proude, petulant: oh <hi>ſifas dicere.</hi> She came naked into the Citty and ſhall returne naked out of the citty, vnles ſhe doe pennance with a white ſheete pind about her when ſhe is dead, as ſhe deſerueth now ſhe liueth. Her Mother is very
<pb facs="tcp:10696:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>well knowne for a poore woman, but I thinke ſhe neuer knew her father. My honeſt maiſter married her for loue, and had nought with her, and he is likely to haue nought ſo long at he hath her: yet ſhe flaunteth with the fineſt, and gaddeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade with the giddieſt: looketh for greater ſeruice then an Empreſſe: and more duty then a Dutches: enuying all that are more brauely trapped then her ſelfe, and confederates with few, but ſuch as are wantonly entrapped as ſhe is. Her Wenches feele the weight of her light fingers, and we haue many a peale wrong about our eares too: We waite all the day to ſerue our maiſters Chapmen, but when any of her Cuſtomers come, we are ſent abroade on a ſleeueleſſe errand, and then what becomes of our maiſters ware? I doe now wiſh that ſome faire Chaunce may light vpon her, to rid my ſuſpectleſſe maiſter of ſo foule a miſchiefe, both for his owne ſake and welfare, and the future quietneſſe of his tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie Seruants. But to all good Miſtreſſes, whoſe conditions are contrary to hers, I do wiſh <hi>Fortune</hi> to poure vpon them the aboundance of her fauours.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The Prentiſe.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Mal-content walketh along.</head>
               <p>VVEll ſaid yong Prentiſe, <hi>Macte tua virtute puer, Sici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ad aſtra.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contene.</note> Procéed as thou haſt begun, and doubt not to become a good Common weales-man, when thou haſt gotten thée a bigger purſe, a better office, and a larger beard. Another ioggeth along, ſpurning the pauement as if he were angry with it. For ſhame let not thine hat hang ouer thine eyes? Doſt thou diſpaire of thy face, thou maskſt it ſo with thy cloake? hold vp thine head like a man: and pinne thy band thou ſlouen; Button thy wriſts, it is wholeſome, and garter thy ſtockings it is hanſome.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Opinion of the Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content.</note>His thoughts (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) are as confuſed, as his appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell: he brabieth with his ſtarres, &amp; brauleth at his creation: he wiſheth the Caule which wrapped him in his mothers
<pb facs="tcp:10696:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>wombe, had bene his winding ſhéete: and he which breathed that <hi>Promotheon</hi> fire into him, had put it out. The welfare of others is his bane, and their ruine <hi>Balſamum</hi> to him: He thinks better of himſelfe then he diſerneth, and worſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers then they demerit: He proacheth that which he will not follow, &amp; followes that which no true Chriſtian will preach: his words are lightning, which though they alight vpon all, yet they fire few: what he thinketh, he bolteth out without charity. He wipeth vices taile with his tongue, and that is the reaſon his words are ſo vnſauory. He is like a bauling dog, that barks at all that gallops on horſebach, when he goes a foote: like a mad dogge that ſnappeth at all that méete him: like a maſtiffe that worrieth oftentimes ſuch as come neare him. He is other mens foe, and none of his own friend: he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liketh both extreames, and thinketh meanely of the meane: he is a <hi>Miſanthropos,</hi> which hateth men, a <hi>Narciſſus</hi> which loueth not women, a <hi>Diogenes</hi> which carpeth at all, a maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Mal-content.</p>
               <div type="petition">
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Mal-contents Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition.</note>If you tender the welfare of a Diſcontent, whoſe perturbed Spirit, haunteth you in this white ſheete, poure downe your diſaſtrous accidents vpon the worlds waſters, diſorders, vice, and villany. Say this Petition be preiudiciall to many: many haue ſtradled ouer the like ſtyle, and more would walke in the ſame path, were they not extruded and excluded. What rare <hi>Machiauils</hi> (right matchleſſe villaines) how many be dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the <hi>Barathrum</hi> of beggery, ſo they be mounted vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the heauen of honour? What remorſe hath a reprobate who ſtarue and want cloathing, ſo he be full fed, and gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geouſly arrayed? I am no Spaniell to fawne vpon men, nor little Puppy to licke the excrements of women. The Diuell domineereth like a great commander, and his ſouldiers march vnder the colour of honeſty, which now a dayes is accounted like a ſtrumpet, <hi>He which vſeth it ſhal die a begger.</hi> Couetouſnes is become a Tradeſman, and Pride his wife. Drunkennes the onely ſociable companion, &amp; Lechery the ſole good fellow: Gluttony is a great man, and Enuy a yonger brother: Sloth
<pb facs="tcp:10696:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath got a liuing: Oh Sodome, thou waſt fired for thy ſinnes, yet thy ſinnes eſcaped, and range <hi>hic &amp; vbi<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>,</hi> Old Tyre, thou waſt deiected, new tires are erected: <hi>Redit orbis in orbem.</hi> The Aſſe hath got on the Lions skin, luſty Harts caſt their horns a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Faunes: Spiders make their Cobwebs in kings Courts: little Conyes vndermine huge Caſtles, and pull the wals vpon their owne heads: <hi>Omnium rerum viciſsitudo.</hi> Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are become ſlaues: Rich men turnd beggers: Beggers changed to rich men, <hi>Aſperius nihil eſt. Oh tempore, oh mores!</hi> Beaſts he in houſes, Serpents craule in corners, Cookes keepe in citties, Dawes in old Churches, Wag-tailes in great places: Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Vicar is turnd Myner, and doth trafficke with Salt-peeter: <hi>Monſtrum informe, ingens, cui lumen vera pietatis eſt ademptum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The Mal-content.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The poore Scholler walketh by.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The poore Scholler.</note>HE fiſheth finely, and is likely to catch Carpes, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. But what <hi>Mounſier Male-goe</hi> is this, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth next, ſo diſplaying the fretted Cuffe-Taffity facing of his thread bare cloake? Cannot he walke vprightly like an honeſt man, but iet if ſo like a Iennet, and wagge his head to and fro like a Weathercocke? Fie vpon it what Ruſticall logges he maketh like a Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nant, or a countrey Curate, which neuer came any nearer to an Vniuerſity then Lincolne Minſter. <hi>Odit prophanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vulgens,</hi> He is none of your Plebei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in his own conceit, but <hi>Apollos</hi> godſon, chriſtened in the <hi>Pirenean,</hi> or <hi>Hyporrenean</hi> fount, he is a common Souldiour vnder <hi>Mineruas</hi> en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gne, and fighteth like a Grammer ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler with Pen and Inkhorne.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Opinion of a poore Scholler.</note>Oh forbeare (ſaid <hi>Opinion</hi>) doe not beray your owne neſt, turne not ſtudent of the law, &amp; forget your old <hi>Academi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> aſſociates: yet I thinke you ſpeake not this out of malice to the parties, but of meere loue, that they ſeeing their fooliſh gutes gibed at, may amend them: for theere are ſome of your
<pb facs="tcp:10696:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>peart <hi>Iuuenals,</hi> that mince it, as if they were citizens wiues: and yet I will not ſay that it proceedeth from any pride, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer woening conceit in all that do ſo: but of an ill habit, which they haue gotten by a careles and fantaſticall carriage. But let that paſſe, and ile ſhew you what this preſent Petitioner is: to wit, One which though he did neuer eate Porridge in the Innes of Court without a ſpoon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yet he hath made foule ſhift to denoure his dinner in a Colledge without a Trencher; though he cannot carue a Capon without the helpe of a Cleauer, or vnlace a Rabbet like a cunning Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. <hi>Roſtra diſertus amat,</hi> yet he can cate roſt well enough to pleaſe himſelfe. He is a King in his owne conceit: and hath more in him then euery one can conceiue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He deſerueth better ſauour then the world affordeth him: and yet he hath as good fauor as any in the world which hath no better then he hath: How he hath bene eſtimated in former times, it bootes him not, yet he hath Bootes when he rideth, though he borrow them. To be ſhort, and ſerious, he is reice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed of fools, reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the wiſe, held in diſgrace among prophane, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necent reputation with thoſe, which are ſincerely religious. Nothing regarded by the couetous and baſe minded churles, but greatly rewarded by the liberall and truly deſcended Gentilitie, a Scholler.</p>
               <div type="petition">
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The poore Schollers Pention.</note>Would it not grieue that gentleman, which had ſold his ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nories, and ſpent the mony vpon hopes of preferment, and in fine, behold his inferiours aduanced, and himſelfe obtaine no greater reward then faire promiſes and faithles proteſtations? Would it not kill that Souldiers heart with grief, which when he had loſt his limmes, and left his liuing for his Countreys good, returning feeble, and decrepit to his natiue Countrey, to be Caged, Stockt, and baited with Beadles? And would it not pine that Scholler, and make him looke like the vicar of Saint Albones, that hath bene brought vp ſeuen yeares vnder the lanching laſh of a left-handed School-maſter, &amp; after that feed with 3. penny chops, &amp; very ſingular beere in an Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, roſe early, &amp; watched late, <hi>Per tot diſcrimina reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tendimus
<pb facs="tcp:10696:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>ad latium,</hi> thorough many troubles we attayne to Latine, and after all this, to be a poore Pen-an-Inck-horne wearer, a <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagog,</hi> one that teacheth Schollers for 5. pence the weeke, and at the quarter day is glad to take choake-cheeſe, and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell butter for the Summa Totalis: <hi>Proh deum, atque hominum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>idem.</hi> Oh that ſome fellow which had but a little wit, and no wiſdome, migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rauerſe this Parentheſis: Me thinke I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend him already how vnreaſonably he would raile vpon the 7. liberall Sciences, wiſh <hi>Pernaſſus</hi> turn'd to a Molehill, &amp; that <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulcan,</hi> when he claue <hi>Minerua</hi> out of <hi>Iupiters</hi> braine, had knockt out the braines too, becauſe that he carrying the Muſes, as familiars about him, ſhould be pinched with want, when he knoweth many ſeruile groomes, whoſe qualities or dimentions are no way ſurpaſſing his, promoted from the ſtable to the table, from the table to the bed. But hoe there Signiour: Hee that can picke any thing out of a painted cloath, may perceiue by fortune painted muffled in a tree, throwing downe vpon ſome, Crownes: others, military wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons: ſome bagges of Gold, others Sackes of Salt: Some one thing, others another thing: Some muſt be Kings and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule all, ſome muſt be Souldiers, and fight for their Countrey, ſome muſt be husbandmen, and digge commodity from the earth, ſome muſt be Aſtronomers, and plucke proffit from the ſtarres: ſome muſt haue more then they can carry, and ſuch are richmen: ſome muſt be men of good carriage, and can get little, &amp; ſuch are Porters: ſome muſt haue liuings enough bequeathed them, and ſome muſt not haue ſo much as an haire left them: ſome muſt lead the world in a ſtring, and ſome muſt leaue the world in a ſtring: <hi>Quae cum ita ſint</hi> (oh moſt mutable) I doe not grudge at my calamities, but the cauſes: <hi>Aueroas Maecenaſſes</hi> and dunſticall <hi>Dondegoes,</hi> which will allow a Scholler no more, that ſhould waft them to heauen, then a Sculler that ſhould cary them alongſt the Theams, or any other hauens: <hi>Muſas facientes Mulos:</hi> Making the Muſes, Mules, Iades, or Hacknies: For ſuppoſe a Scholler (like olde <hi>Byas</hi>) carrieth all his Lands about him, be intertaynd into any
<pb facs="tcp:10696:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>of their houſes, as many be: Though he be a good Grama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, one that can chop Logick, and like the freſhman, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from <hi>Athens,</hi> make three egges of two, and his father eating the two, bad him take the third for his cunning: ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine he can pretty well in Philoſophy naturall, and metaphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall, tell halfe an hundreth lyes out of Pliny: hath ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight in Poetry, and if he had maintenance and countenance would be come a ſound Practitioner in the deepeſt Science: This fellow for all this ſhal be lodged next the kitchin, where the Cookes, and ſculles keepe ſuch a ſcolding that they will take order for his ſtudying: or in ſome ruynous roome, where his Maſters Fathers Ghoſt is reported to walke: and Robin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>good fellow and Hobgoblins, are ſaid to play their fagayries in the night, ſo that he will take no reſt for ſleeping and all the day he ſhall ſpend himſelfe poaring ouer my <hi>Lady Fayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woulds</hi> capable eldeſt: and three or foure froward (I ſhould ſay toward) younger Brothers: for which turmoyles his yearely ſtipend ſhall be 5. markes, beſides the Patrons, or the Widdowes countenance: Which may be ſo good that few Schollers hauing reaſonable Noſes in their faces, would be loath to haue it for fourty poundes. Now for his fare, it is lightly at the cheefeſt Table, but he muſt ſit vnder the Salt, this is an Axiome in ſuch places: and before he take his ſeat, <hi>Memorandum</hi> he haue two legs in ſtore, one for the Maiſter, another for the Miſtreſſe: Then hauing drawne his Knife leiſurably, vnfoulded his Napkin mannerly, after twice or thrice wyping his Beard (if he haue it) he may reach the Bread on his Knifes point, and fall to his porridge and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene euery Sponefull take as much deliberation, as a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming (leaſt he be out of his porridge before they haue buried part of their firſt courſe in their Bellyes) And at the ſecond ſeruice (if there be any ſuch hot ſeruice) the refuſe of the former ſhall be ſet before him, but oftentimes like a rifled Souldier, hauing not ſo much as a good peece left, or like the picture of death, all bones, which putteth him in minde to decline <hi>bonus, bona, bonum:</hi> but this muſt be vnderſtood to
<pb facs="tcp:10696:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>happen at an hunting dinner, or after he hath whipped his el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Scholler, for ſo long as my young Maiſter liketh his Scholemaiſter, and may take no farther at his leſſon, then he liſt, his mother will be moſt reſpectiue, but if he once con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict him, and prince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>winger vpon his poſteriors, then la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are raiſd, there is an inſurrection amongſt the pen-boys <hi>Peter Prouin</hi> the horſe-keeper will doe, Zauods that he will. The Cooke will put poiſon in his porridge, or worke him ſome other miſchiefe, if he durſt: then enters the Fleire, like the <hi>Chorus</hi> in a Tragedy, and telleth all. The mother like a tender hearted <hi>Auditor,</hi> pittieth the Scene, buſſeth her boy, and telleth him he ſhall be beaten no more, No, that he ſhall not. Thus doth the olde foole hugge young <hi>Iackanapes,</hi> till ſhe ſpoile him: yet heere is not the full <hi>Cataſtrophe,</hi> for ſhe will neuer reſt till ſhe haue lifted him out of her houſe, and will haue another in his roome, it maketh no matter what he be, ſo he will not whippe her boy and ſerue for little wages, he will ſerue the turne: I mary, this maketh ſo many wilde youthes, and wiſe aged men: When the earth is not well manured, tilled and ploughed, it is rancke, and ſterile, and where youth wanteth nurture, age is ignorant, and ill manne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. The Beare by licking her whelpes bringeth them into ſome forme, but many mothers by lolling their children turne them out of all good faſhion. The loue of Parents towards their children is naturall and not to be blamed, but this Coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kering is fond, and hurtfull: Waxe being ſofte, will ſuffer any impreſſion, and children being young are as capable of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, if they be trayned vp therafter: as they are prone to knauery without any great inducements. The Colt at firſt backing will curuet, and winch, but after he hath chancked the bit a while, and felt the Spurfe in his ſide, he becometh more tractable: Not an Hedgeplaſher but can ſay, he which will haue a thorne, muſt cut a thorne, and if they would haue theſe tender plantes to proue godly Columnes in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, let them be lopt, and dreſſed in drie ſeaſon: let them be carefully <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tored, and encouraged by faire meanes,
<pb facs="tcp:10696:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>and reaſonable recreation: If that will not worke with them, vſe a ſtronger potion: <hi>Qui non vult / duci, debet / trahi,</hi> He that will not goe gently, muſt be dragged vncourteouſly: The tranquill gouernement of our commonwealth doth ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently manifeſt, how much our Land is bleſſed with a thrice worthy King: prouident Counſell, vpright Iudges, learned and well educated Gentlemen, zealous Diuines, any cunning Lawiers enow, yet it may be obſerued in ſome places where many are congregated about publique affaires, others ſhuffled in, which whilſt the others are poiſing the weightieſt matters, fit like Cyphers, and if any queſtion be put vnto them. <hi>Obmutuerunt; Putas ne verhum potuiſſe proloqui:</hi> They can tell the Clocke daudle their gloues, or play with their forepoints, their Mothers taught them thoſe Leſſons, when they ſatte playing with them vpon their Knees: They thinke they pleaſure their Countrey, if they vouchſafe their preſence, and grace themſelues, if they put of the hatte hanſomely, and nod the head with a Clowdy countenance, as who would ſay, it is an hard caſe, but <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erbum non amplius:</hi> And what is the cauſe of this, but whilſt the one kept cloſe at their bookes both at home and abroad in the Vniuerſity and Innes of Court, the other were yalping after a Kennel of Hounds, in their youth, or whoping at an Owle in an Iuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſh. Their parents would not be at the coſt to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a good Scholler to traine them vp, nor their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſuffer them to indure any hardeneſſe, or labour: without which true knowledge cannot be attained: And as many of theſe are careleſſe for the well educating of their children: So moſt of them are ſupine and negligent of themſelues. What careth the couetous Patron, to he can compound to his contentement: Be he one of Bale Prieſts, or a bald Prieſt, if he can read the Authoriſed Seruice: Be he of what Tribe he will, if he can hoble ouer an homily with a weekes warning: As for monethly Sermons, it is but greaſing a Parater, and the
<pb facs="tcp:10696:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>Churchwarden, is his Tennant: he will be ſworne on a booke <hi>to an owne bene: Infoelix oh ſemper ouis.</hi> Too many places are full of ſuch, which are more meete to be fiſhermen, then fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhers of men, and fitter to catch ſoales, then, ſoules, which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther behaue themſelues like the dogge in the Manger, which neither would eat hay himſelfe, nor ſuffer the beaſt: Which either keepe the childrens bread from them, or if they giue them any, they doe ſo mouth it, and mangle it, that it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth moſt loathſome, comming from ſuch filthy hands, and handling, which I wiſh were otherwiſe, that the pouerties of poure Schollers might be pittied, their Petitions preferred, their fortunes bettered, &amp; what is amiſſe, might be amended.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The poore Scholler.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>The Scholler hath fruſtrated my expectation (ſaid I) for I did expect he ſhould haue wiſhed ill lucke to light vpon his enemies as the others haue. Touching his ſpeech I durſt auerre it to be true: for drones driue out the Bees, and the wolues in ſheeps cloathing werry the Lambes: They take the tythes, though they take not the paines. Amongſt all which I thinke it reaſon, that that Parſon ſhould haue tyth poridge, which out of the heat of a good ſtomacke (I iudge it was) taught his pariſhioners wines in a quarterly Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fower wayes to keele a pot, when it began to ſeeth ouer: A right worthy domeſticall Chaplin for <hi>Helihogabalus,</hi> yet if yow marke, it is a profitable diſh of doctrine, for vnleſſe it be fellowed, all the fat is in the fire: But how now? who commeth next? There are many <hi>Petitioners</hi> behinde. How chaunce they ſteppe not forward? I perceiue the Beadle is angry, and will ſuffer no more to be preferred or brought into the Citty, till anſwer be made to the reſt that are already <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hibited.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:10696:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A PROSOPOPAEI A OR IMAGINED ANSWER TO THE FORMER PETITIO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. by Dame Fortune</head>
            <lg>
               <l>NO more Petitions, I haue heard too much,</l>
               <l>Too miſ chieuous, and monſtrous wickedneſſe,</l>
               <l>Nor will I condeſcend to any ſuch</l>
               <l>As ſeeke by others woe to purchace bliſſe:</l>
               <l>Your ſuites ſo wicked, your Petitions full</l>
               <l>O ſenſuall appetites, I diſanull.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fond worldlings, thinke you, that euery furious curſe</l>
               <l>Belcht gainſt your foes, ſhall bring them to their wracke?</l>
               <l>Or euery fooliſh wiſh your fancies nurſe,</l>
               <l>Will with an approbation be ſent backe?</l>
               <l>Then ſhould the world be as it firſt began,</l>
               <l>Repleate with beaſts, but diſpoſſeſt of man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For as you are by naturall inſtinct</l>
               <l>Infirme, and ſubiect to affections:</l>
               <l>So are your wilfull Supplications linckt</l>
               <l>With others ruines, and fubuerſions:</l>
               <l>But he that knoweth beſt whats good, whats <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Payes all, not as they would, but as he will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And therefore know, that whoſocre you curſe,</l>
               <l>Are not accurſed for your curſe alone,</l>
               <l>Nor they whom you wiſh puniſhments, are worſe</l>
               <l>For your raſh wiſhes publicke or vnknowne:</l>
               <l>Nor I my ſelfe, if that I would, can doe</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:10696:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Hurt to the parties, you incite me to.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For that <hi>Ens Entium,</hi> all the worlds firſt maker,</l>
               <l>Exiſtent without fine, and vncreate</l>
               <l>Makes any thing the cauſe and ioynt pertaker</l>
               <l>Of his confuming rage to ruinate</l>
               <l>His chiefeſt earthly fabricke, when and where</l>
               <l>He pleaſe, it from a ſinfull earth to teare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus much ingenerall: Now I will regreſſe</l>
               <l>More ſpecially to each particular,</l>
               <l>And as you did appeare at firſt, redreſſe,</l>
               <l>To here your anſwers, which Ile not deferre</l>
               <l>With dull procraſtinations, but begin</l>
               <l>With her, who firſt put her Petition in.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">The anſwer to the Harrlot</note>Deteſted woman, ſhame vnto thy Sexe,</l>
               <l>Which proſtitut'ſt thy body vnto all,</l>
               <l>Making thy ſelfe the filth and loathſome fex</l>
               <l>That brings thine owne decay and others thrall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Leaue of thy loathed trading, and be bound</l>
               <l>A new to honeſty, thats ſafe and ſound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Conſider why thou wert created firſt</l>
               <l>To ſerue thy Maker, and bring forth in creaſe,</l>
               <l>From which, thy loathed life, and quenchles thirſt</l>
               <l>Of variable luſt, compels thee ceaſe.</l>
               <l>For thy foule life ſo odious in heauens eye</l>
               <l>Can leaue the world no proſperous progeny.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Next call to minde the pleaſures thou haſt paſt,</l>
               <l>The dainty fare, ſweet muſicke, and delight,</l>
               <l>How momentarily and ſoone they waſt,</l>
               <l>Like to a flaſh of lightning in the night,</l>
               <l>Or like a Larke, that ſwiftly mounts the skie,</l>
               <l>Now ſeene, but out of proſpect by and by.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:10696:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>And laſt of all, thinke but vpon thine end,</l>
               <l>When Age begins to neſtle in thy bones,</l>
               <l>What anguiſhes thy former courſes ſend,</l>
               <l>Fraught with heart-waſting aches, pangs and grones:</l>
               <l>And after all, how thou art ſure to fry,</l>
               <l>If thou doſt perſeuere, eternally.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou which haſt lauiſht thy eſtate, and ſpent</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">To the Spen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall.</note>Thy prime of time, in vnaduiſ'd exceſſe,</l>
               <l>Do not miſpend the refidue thats lent</l>
               <l>To cure thy cares, and driue thee from diſtreſſe:</l>
               <l>If thou haſt grace, ther's grace inough in ſtore,</l>
               <l>For him that truly can that grace implore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Luſt, Pride and Riot, wreſtling in thy breſt,</l>
               <l>Haue giuen thy Fortunes, and thy ſelfe the fall,</l>
               <l>Yet lie not groueling with diſpaire oppreſt,</l>
               <l>Although thou canſt not all tha's paſt recall,</l>
               <l>Thou maiſt redeeme that thou haſt pawn'd to hell,</l>
               <l>Thy pittious ſoule hereafter, liuing well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou country Client with inuectiue Iawes,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">To the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Client.</note>Darting thy malice and inteſtine griefe,</l>
               <l>Vpon ſome bad peruerters of the Lawes,</l>
               <l>Shalt eaſe thy ſelfe and purchace great reliefe,</l>
               <l>By ſhunning the occaſions of thy fals,</l>
               <l>Vncharitable deeds, lirigious brauls.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If thou wouldſt haue reuenge vpon them all,</l>
               <l>Liue orderly, deuoyd of wrong and ſtrife:</l>
               <l>So maiſt thou ſuch contentious wrangles gall,</l>
               <l>By leading a contented and mylde life:</l>
               <l>For while each petty treſpaſſe, brawl and taunt,</l>
               <l>Are tooke in ſnuffe and dudgeon, Lawyers fla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Seruingman came next, which hath reuilde</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:10696:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>The ſlight rewarding of his youthfull paines,</l>
               <l>Though ſome that truſt to others, are beguild,</l>
               <l>Yet faithfull ſeruice oft reaps certaine gaines,</l>
               <l>Ingratitude if rife, yet there are ſuch</l>
               <l>That deeme no guerdon for their ſeruants much.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſeeing thou felſt (as thy Petition ſhowes)</l>
               <l>Betweene the griping clawes of auerous churles,</l>
               <l>Impatient ſpeech, proclaim'd againſt all thoſe.</l>
               <l>To further inconuence hurles</l>
               <l>Thy deſperate ſtate: how ere it did commence,</l>
               <l>Tak't as thy ſinnes deſerued recompence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou, which wert credulous to iudge all true</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">To the Maide with childe.</note>A yong man vttered in the heate of blood,</l>
               <l>So piteouſly doſt now too late bedew</l>
               <l>Thy cheeks with teares: it is a token good.</l>
               <l>If they do trickle from a ſorrowing ſoule,</l>
               <l>Not for thy Loues loſſe, but thy deeds ſo foule.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where ſores are cureles, ther's no helpe by care</l>
               <l>Content will mittigrate each Diſcontent,</l>
               <l>Kept as a ſhield to ward thee from Diſpaire,</l>
               <l>And fierce aſſaults of future languiſhment,</l>
               <l>The cauſer cannot thriue: vvhat heretofore</l>
               <l>You did commit, Repent: but ſinne no more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You are too hot, too eager, and to keene</l>
               <l>Gainſt thoſe you loue ſo well, the female kinde,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">To the Loue:</note>Bolting outragious termes, oreclog'd with ſpleene,</l>
               <l>From the diſtracted paſſions of your minde,</l>
               <l>Sincerely vertuous, many may be found,</l>
               <l>Though ſome with many vices do abound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> wrong'd you, wrong not all for one</l>
               <l>Nor dote on her, that hath forſaken you,</l>
               <l>One precious ſtone doth out another ſtone,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:10696:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Thers plenty yet abroad, goe get a new,</l>
               <l>Seeke with diſcretion, and doubt not to finde</l>
               <l>A conſtant Mate, that may content thy minde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">To he olde woman mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with the young man.</note>Old woman, leaue complayning, 'tis too late</l>
               <l>For you to lodge within a youngſters bed,</l>
               <l>You are decrepit, and growne out of date</l>
               <l>To reyne a ſlinging Coles, vnweldy head</l>
               <l>A prayer booke linckt to your ſhaking hands</l>
               <l>Were fitter farre then youngeſt wedlocke bandes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">To the young woman mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to the old man</note>Doe not repine, or grudge, young louely creature</l>
               <l>At vneſcaped Deſtiny, Mariage:</l>
               <l>Nor macerate with cares your beauteous feature</l>
               <l>Banning cannot abate your griefe, nor rage</l>
               <l>Not any other thing ſalue your diſeaſe,</l>
               <l>Vntill the cutting Deſtiny doth pleaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Imagine that thou art a weaned childe</l>
               <l>Hugd in the boſome of an aged nurſe</l>
               <l>Let deeds and wordes be dutifull and milde</l>
               <l>Leaſt they doe make thy anguiſhes the worſe,</l>
               <l>For in a moment Age with Rage is toſt</l>
               <l>And waxeth moſt impatient, being croſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">To the Cuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>Thou that Petition'ſt gainſt thy wiues offence</l>
               <l>Se thou be cleere thy ſelfe of the like ſpot,</l>
               <l>Then maiſt thou with more right thy ſuite commence,</l>
               <l>Or els take quietly thy crooked lot,</l>
               <l>For he that ſtri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es with Sword, it is decreed</l>
               <l>Shall be reſtruck with Scabberd, till he bleed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Iome Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier.</note>Couragious Souldier, whoſe true valorous heart</l>
               <l>Was neuer daunted with inuading foes</l>
               <l>But could thy greateſt enemies to ſtart</l>
               <l>(At thy aſſayling them) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>morous Doos</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:10696:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Vanquiſh thy ſelfe, and chance which puls thee downe</l>
               <l>A thing more mighty then to winne a Towne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Liue carefully young Prentiſe, be no waſter</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">To the Pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</note>Of others goods, abandon filthy whores,</l>
               <l>And diſſolute aſſemblies: Pleaſe thy Maiſter</l>
               <l>And all the night keepe cloſe within his dores,</l>
               <l>Roue not about the ſuburbes and the ſtreetes</l>
               <l>When he doth thinke you wrapt betweene your ſheets.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Too many take ſuch courſes vile and baſe</l>
               <l>To their owne miſeries and maiſters fall</l>
               <l>But if thou doe thy duty in thy place</l>
               <l>And prouidently keepe within thy ſtall,</l>
               <l>When they ride bound, or lurke in ſome by-lnae</l>
               <l>Thou maiſt ride with thy foot-cloth, and gold chaine,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">To the Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content.</note>Thou that in vaine doſt wrangle with thy ſtarres,</l>
               <l>And cauill at the factes by others done,</l>
               <l>Leaue of thy ſelfe-deſtroying ciuill warres,</l>
               <l>And intermedling with all others, ſhunne,</l>
               <l>Enormeties enow thou haſt to mend</l>
               <l>If to thine owne affaires thou doe deſcend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And to conclude, let all for certaine know</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">To all.</note>That Gods reuengefull Yron Bowe is bent</l>
               <l>And ſhaftes in readines to ouerthrow</l>
               <l>Synnes harbourers, that doe not ſoone repent,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let each one therefore his vilde courſes mend,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A wicked life makes ſeldome a good end.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>With that, me thought, I ſaw Fortune trnaſported out of ſight, &amp; the Petitioners made ſuch an huming at her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, as if it had beene at the applauſiue end of an Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity oration, or other Scholler like exerciſe, that they awaked me with the noyſe, who in the end, writ the premiſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:10696:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
